<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panoplia, or, Armour of proof for a weak Christian, against the worlds envy, scoffs and reproaches together with the doves innocency and the serpents subtility, upon Gen. 3. 15. / by R.J. [sic]</title>
            <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 129 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y167C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43836</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475301</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475301</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97253)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2260:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panoplia, or, Armour of proof for a weak Christian, against the worlds envy, scoffs and reproaches together with the doves innocency and the serpents subtility, upon Gen. 3. 15. / by R.J. [sic]</title>
                  <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third impression.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Younge by WIng (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Running title: A glasse for scorners, or, Instruction to prevent destruction.</note>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, John Downame." -- p. 36.</note>
                  <note>"At the Blew Pales, over against the High Constables short of Shoreditch Church; where is a Glasse Lanthorn in the Window: such as please may have them." -- p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, worn, and tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151476:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151476:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PANOPLIA:</hi> OR, Armour of Proof FOR A WEAK CHRISTIAN, Againſt the worlds envy, ſcoffs and reproaches. Together with the <hi>Doves</hi> Innocency and the <hi>Serpents</hi> ſubtilty, upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. The third Impreſſion. By <hi>R.J.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome time ſince I heard you upon 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, neither Fornicators, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor no unrighteous perſons, ſhall ever inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> What change it hath wrought in me, I forbear to mention: But certainly <hi>Satan</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> fear they have loſt, the one a <hi>ſubject</hi> or <hi>priſoner,</hi> the other a <hi>limbe</hi> or <hi>member</hi> ever ſince: for whereas they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er moleſted me for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; now as if I were reſcued out of <hi>Satans</hi> clu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es, that <hi>Lyon</hi> foames and roares, and beſtirs himſelf to recover his loſſe.</p>
               <p>And as for my old acquaintance, they ſo envy to ſee themſelves caſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſo mortally hate me, for that <hi>I will no longer</hi> continue miſerable, nor <hi>run with them</hi> (as I have done) <hi>to the ſame exceſſe of riot,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.4. that they make me <hi>weary of my life,</hi> as the <hi>daughters of Heth</hi> did <hi>Rebecka,</hi> Gen. 27.46.</p>
               <p>Yea I am ſo ſcoft at and ſcorned, both by <hi>Parents, Friends</hi> and <hi>Enemies,</hi> that it not only hinders me from doing the good I would, or appearing the ſame I am; but it almoſt beats me off from being religious back to the <hi>world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And certainly he muſt be more <hi>ſpirit</hi> then <hi>fleſh,</hi> that can contentedly make himſelf contemptible to follow <hi>Chriſt;</hi> be pointed at for ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, endure ſo many baſe and vile nick-names; have his Religion judged hypocriſie, his godly ſimplicity fillineſſe, his zeal madneſſe, his contempt of the world ignorance, his godly ſorrow dumpiſhneſſe, and the like mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and miſchievous conſtructions made of whatſoever he ſpeaks or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151476:2"/>does. For my part, I could better abide <hi>a ſtake</hi> (God aſſiſting me) then the mocks, ſcoffs and ſcornes which every where I meet withall. It is death to me to be mockt; as it fared with <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> Jer. 38.19. Nor is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Hell</hi> a greater puniſhment in my judgement, then to become a <hi>Saunio,</hi> a ſubject of ſcorn, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> (I doubt not) found. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> profeſt, that neither the proſcription of his goods, nor his baniſhment, not the wounds he received in his body, were ſo grievous to him as one ſcornfull word from his enemy <hi>Cteſiphon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea doubtleſle our <hi>Saviours</hi> ear was more painfully pierced, then either his brows, or hands, or feet. It could not but go deep into his ſoul, to hear thoſe bitter and girding reproaches from them whom he came to ſave: A generous nature is more wounded with the tongue then with the hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>I Grant there is no ſuch rub in the way to <hi>Heaven</hi> as this;<note place="margin">Miniſter</note> 
                  <hi>Satan</hi> hath not ſuch a tried <hi>ſhaft</hi> in all his <hi>quiver:</hi> he gets more now by ſuch diſcouragements, and the reproaches that are caſt upon Religion, then he did formerly by <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>faggot;</hi> for then the <hi>blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> was found to be <hi>the ſeed of the Church:</hi> others (<hi>Phaenix</hi> like) ſpringing out of their aſhes: Whereas now, multitudes of ſouls are ſcoft out of their Religion by wicked men; many being apt with <hi>Peter</hi> to deny their religion, when they come in company with <hi>Chriſts</hi> enemies; and with <hi>David</hi> to diſſemble their faith when they are amongſt <hi>Philiſtius,</hi> leſt they ſhould be mockt, have ſo many frowns, and frumps, and cenſures, and ſcoffs; be branded with that odious and ſtigmaticall name of an <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> &amp;c. Yea S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> confeſſeth, that he often belied himſelf with ſins which he never committed, leſt he ſhould be unacceptable to his ſinfull companions; which makes our <hi>Saviour</hi> pronounce <hi>that man bleſsed that is not offended in him,</hi> Matth. 11.6.</p>
               <p>But for all that, a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an will not be ſcoft out of his Money, nor a juſt man flowted out of his Faith. The taunts of an <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſhall never make an <hi>Iſaack</hi> out of love with his <hi>inheritance.</hi> Yea for a man to be ſcoft out of his goodneſſe by thoſe which are lewd, is all one, as if a man that ſeeth ſhould blindefold himſelf or put out his eyes, becauſe ſome blinde wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches revile and ſcoff at him for ſeeing. Or as if one that is ſound of limbes, ſhould limp or maim himſelf to pleaſe the criple, and avoid his taunts, And know this, That if the <hi>barking</hi> of theſe <hi>currs,</hi> ſhall hinder us from walking on our way to <hi>Heaven,</hi> it is a ſign we are moſt impotent cowards: Yea if our love be ſo cold to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that we are aſhamed for his ſake to bear a few ſcoffs and reproaches from the world, it is evident we are but counterfets, ſuch as <hi>Chriſt will be aſhamed of before his Father and his holy Angels as the latter day,</hi> Mark. 8.38. For, for the comfort of all that are ſingle and honeſt-hearted, notwithſtanding all the ſcoffs and ſcorns of <hi>atheists</hi> and careleſſe worldlings, all their perſwaſions and perſecutions, they ſhall both loſe their labours and themſelves too in the end. Well may they intend, and alſo do their utmoſt to flout us out of our Faith, that ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151476:2"/>they may ſlay us with death eternall, and ſpeed thereafter; (As <hi>God</hi> that regards not ſo much what is performed, as what was intended, and meaſures what we do by what we meant to do; as in the caſe of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams offering up his ſonne,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> who only thought they had killed <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 14.19.) but they ſhall be no more able to hinder the ſalvation of any one whom <hi>God</hi> hath choſen to his <hi>Kingdom of grace and glory,</hi> then <hi>Saul</hi> with his <hi>Courtiers</hi> could hinder <hi>David</hi> from attaining the promiſed <hi>Kingdom of Iſrael,</hi> Pſal. 129.1. Revel. 13.8. The windes may well toſſe the <hi>ſhip</hi> wherein <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, but never overturn it. If <hi>Chriſt</hi> have but once poſſeſt the affections, there is no diſpoſſeſſing him again. The League that <hi>Heaven</hi> hath made <hi>Hell</hi> wants power to break. Who can ſeparate the conjunctions of the <hi>Deitie? Whom God did predeſtinate,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, them be alſo called; and whom he called, them he alſo juſtified; and whom he juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, them he alſo glorified,</hi> Rom. 8.30. They ſhall ſooner blow up <hi>hell</hi> with trains of powder, then break the chain of this dependent truth. No power of <hi>men</hi> or <hi>devils</hi> is able to withſtand the will of <hi>God,</hi> it ſhall ſtand firmer then the firmament.</p>
               <p>A fire in the heart overcomes all other fires without: as we ſee in the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> which when the ſweet doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> had once got into their hearts, it could not be got out again by all the torments that wit and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty could deviſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>BUt how ſhould I a <hi>novice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Convert.</note> a <hi>punie,</hi> a <hi>white-liver,</hi> a <hi>milkſop,</hi> ſhak off this ſlaviſh yoak of bondage and fear in which <hi>Satan</hi> for the preſent holds me?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miniſter.</hi> By well obſerving what the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in this caſe hold forth for the encouragement of all that thus ſuffer. I will commend to your ſerious conſideration only ſix things, and I pray minde them well; for <hi>Virgil</hi> moſt excellently and profoundly, couples the <hi>knowledge of cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>conqueſt of all fears</hi> together.</p>
               <p>Firſt obſerve, that grievous temptations and perſecutions, do alwayes accompany the remiſſion of ſinnes. That all men, as <hi>Auſtins</hi> ſpeaks, are neceſſitated to miſeries, who bend their courſe towards the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> neither can <hi>Gods love</hi> be enjoyed without <hi>Satans</hi> diſturbance. Yea the <hi>world</hi> and the <hi>devill</hi> therefore <hi>hate us, becauſe God hath choſen us.</hi> If a convert comes home, the <hi>Angels</hi> welcome him with ſongs, the <hi>devils</hi> follow him with uprore and fury, his old acquaintance with ſcorns and oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, as you ſufficiently finde. Godly men are thorns in wicked mens eyes, as <hi>Job</hi> was in the <hi>devils,</hi> becauſe they are good, or for that they are dearly beloved of <hi>God.</hi> If a mans perſon and wayes pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>world</hi> will be diſpleaſed with both: whence we are ſo often foretold and forewarned of it, that we may be the better forearmed and prepared to entertain it: <hi>All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.12. <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men and nations for my Names ſake,</hi> Matth. 10.22. and 24.9. <hi>Behold I ſend you forth, as ſheep in the midſt of wolves.</hi> Matth. 10.16. and many the like. Whence alſo thoſe many and ſtrong encouragements in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151476:3"/>the <hi>word,</hi> which may ſerve as ſo many flaggons of wine, to comfort and ſtrengthen us againſt whatſoever we meet withall in the <hi>world: Bleſſed are they that ſuffer perſecution for righteouſneſse ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Matth. 5.10. <hi>Bleſsed are ye when men ſhall revile you and perſecute you, and ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake. Rejoyce and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which were before you,</hi> ver. 11, 12. <hi>Rejoyce, inaſmuch as ye are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings; that when his glory ſhall be revealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding joy. For if ye be reproached for the Name of Chriſt, happy are ye. For the ſpirit of glory and of God resteth upon you, which on their part is evil ſpoken of, but on your part is glorified,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.12, 13, 14. Loe here is reward enough, for all that <hi>men</hi> or <hi>devils</hi> can do againſt us; which hath made thouſands even ambitious to imbrace the flames. Your cruelty is our glory, ſaid the <hi>Martyrs</hi> in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time to their perſecutors, for the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we are put to it, the greater ſhall our reward be in <hi>Heaven.</hi> It is to my loſſe (ſaid <hi>Gordius</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi>) if you bate me any thing of my ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: See more <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.28, 29. Rev. 2.13.</p>
               <p>And ſo much to ſhew, that he refuſeth to be an <hi>Abel,</hi> whom the malice of <hi>Cain</hi> doth not exerciſe, as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeaks: For it is an everlaſting rule of the Apoſtle, <hi>He that is born after the fleſh, will perſecute him that is born after the spirit</hi> (Gal. 4.29) not becauſe he is evill, but becauſe he is ſo much better then himſelf, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Becauſe his life is not like other mens, his waies are of another faſhion,</hi> Wiſd. 2.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>SEcondly conſider, That as wee are every where in the <hi>word</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned of it, ſo it is not our caſe alone; for ſearch the whole <hi>Bible</hi> over, and you ſhall not finde one holy man mentioned, without mention of ſomething he ſuffered from ungodly men; as it were eaſie to inſtance, how <hi>Abel, Lot, Noah,</hi> righteous men; <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; <hi>Iſaac, Jacob, Ioſeph; Patriarchs</hi> and Fathers of the <hi>Church;</hi> meek <hi>Moſes,</hi> upright <hi>Samuel, Job</hi> that none-ſuch, all the <hi>Lords Prieſts, Prophets, Apoſtles;</hi> yea the harmleſſe <hi>Babes,</hi> and our <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> himſelf did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally ſuffer from wicked and ungodly men. Yea never man came to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> but firſt he paſt through this <hi>purgatory. God</hi> had one ſonne without ſinne, but never any one without ſuffering. Which makes our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſay, <hi>Woe be to you when all men ſpeak well of you,</hi> that is, when evil men ſpeak well of you; <hi>for ſo did the Jews of the falſe Prophets,</hi> Luk. 6.26. Wherefore <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell not though the world hate you,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Neither count it ſtrange,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> hath it, <hi>concerning the fiery triall, which is amongſt you to try you, as though ſome ſtrange thing were come unto you,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.12. For <hi>Chriſt and his Croſse</hi> are inſeparable, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.27. Whence that diſtinction of <hi>Luther,</hi> that <hi>a Chriſtian</hi> is <hi>a Croſſe-bearer. He that will be my diſciple, let him take up his croſſe daily and follow me,</hi> Luk. 9.23. and 14 26, 27.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THirdly, No hope it ſhould be otherwiſe, ſince <hi>God</hi> from the beginning of the Creation, hath proclaimed a War, enmity and ſtrife, between
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151476:3"/>the wicked and the godly: Did you never read that Scripture, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15? where <hi>God</hi> himſelf ſaith to the <hi>Serpent, I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed and her ſeed; he,</hi> or it, <hi>ſhall bruſe thine head, and thou ſhalt bruſe his heel.</hi> Where by the <hi>ſerpents ſeed,</hi> are meant the whole generation of wicked men; and by the <hi>womans ſeed, Chriſt</hi> and all his <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> as all Interpreters conclude and other Scriptures make cleere; where <hi>wicked men</hi> are called <hi>ſerpents, a generation of vipers,</hi> and <hi>children of the devil,</hi> Matth. 23.33. Joh. 8.44. 1 Joh. 3.10. And as this war was proclaimed in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> even in the beginning of time, (<hi>originall ſinne</hi> being the originall of this diſcord) ſo it ſhall continue to the end of all time: When time, ſaith One, began, this malice firſt began, nor will it end but with the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt man. It is an everlaſting <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> like a <hi>Statute</hi> in <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> Which is the next thing I would commend to your ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: And that you may be the better confirmed therein, ſee how according to the Lords prediction or proclamation, there hath been a perpetuall war, enmity and ſtrife in all ages paſt, is now and ever ſhall be, between <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and their <hi>Regiments</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> and the <hi>godly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For proof whereof I could produce teſtimonies and examples innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, there being ſcarce a page in the <hi>Bible,</hi> which doth not expreſſe or imply ſomewhat touching this enmity. But that I may be brief, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>examples</hi> give a quicker impreſſion then <hi>arguments,</hi> I will only give you three inſtances in every Age. As</p>
               <p>Firſt, to begin with the <hi>firſt Age,</hi> viz. the <hi>old world</hi> before the <hi>flood.</hi> We read of this mortall enmity and ſtrife between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.12. between <hi>Lamech</hi> and the <hi>holy ſeed,</hi> Gen. 4.23, 24. and between thoſe wicked <hi>Giants</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes of, and the <hi>ſons of God,</hi> Gen. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>2, to 12. Yea thoſe <hi>Giants</hi> bad battell to <hi>Heaven,</hi> as our <hi>Mythologiſts</hi> add to <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>After the Flood,</hi> before the <hi>Law,</hi> between all the <hi>men of Sodom</hi> and righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> Gen. 19.4.9.11. 2 Pet. 2.8. Between <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael; the bond-woman and her ſonne,</hi> and <hi>Sarah and Iſaac, the free<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>woman and her ſonne,</hi> Gen. 21.9, 10. Gal. 4.29. and between <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> firſt in the womb, the more plainly to ſhaddow out this enmity, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22, 23. and after they were born, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>After the Law,</hi> before <hi>Christ,</hi> between <hi>Doeg</hi> and the 85 <hi>Prieſts</hi> which he <hi>ſlew with the edge of the ſword,</hi> 1 Sam. 22 18, 19. between <hi>Jezabel</hi> and all the <hi>Prophets of the Lord</hi> which ſhe deſtroyed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.13, 14. and between the <hi>heads of Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Micaiahs</hi> time, and <hi>all that were good,</hi> Mich. 3.2.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Since the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in the time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> this enmity ſo manifeſted it ſelf not only in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but in the <hi>Jews Gods</hi> own people, who firſt raiſed thoſe perſecutions againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his members; that having beheaded <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> his harbinger, and crucified himſelf the <hi>Lord of life:</hi> We reade that of all the twelve, none died a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death ſave only S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John,</hi> and he alſo was baniſhed by <hi>Domitian</hi> to <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> and at another time thruſt into a <hi>Tun of ſeething oyl</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> do report: See <hi>Acts</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>51, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o 60. and 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to 5. <hi>Rom,</hi> 8.36. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.18, 19.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151476:4"/>
               <p> Fifthly, After the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> if we conſider the reſidue of the <hi>ten Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> raiſed by the <hi>Romans</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which was for three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, till the coming of godly <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> we finde that under <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian,</hi> ſeventeen thouſand <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were ſlain in one moneth, amongſt whom was <hi>Serena</hi> the <hi>Empereſſe</hi> alſo. Yea under him and nine other <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,</hi> there was ſuch an innumerable company of innocent <hi>Christians</hi> put to death and tormented, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Chromatius</hi> and <hi>Heleod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith, There is no one day in the year, unto which the number of five thouſand <hi>Martyrs</hi> might not be aſcribed, except only the firſt day of <hi>January.</hi> Yea there was two thouſand ſuffered in the ſame place and at the ſame time with <hi>Nicanor,</hi> Acts and Monuments <hi>pag.</hi> 32. who were put to the moſt exquiſite deaths and torments, that ever the wit or malice of men or devils could invent to inflict upon them, and all for profeſſing the faith of <hi>Christ</hi> and being holy: which makes S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> cry out, <hi>I think that God hath ſet forth us the last Apoſtles, as men appointed to death!</hi> 1 Cor. 4.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>SIxtly, From the <hi>Primitive times</hi> and infancy of the <hi>Church</hi> hitherto; the <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> have acted their parts in ſhedding the blood of the <hi>Saints,</hi> as well as the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Roman Emperours;</hi> touching which I will refer you to the Book of <hi>Acts and Monuments:</hi> and <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. <hi>The whore of Babylon was drunk with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> ver. 6. Which in part was fulfilled in <hi>England</hi> under the reign of Queen <hi>Mary:</hi> and in <hi>France,</hi> where before many late bloody maſſacres, there were more then two hundred thouſand who ſuffered Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom about <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> See <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory,</hi> lib. 6. cap. 4, 5, 16. But</p>
               <p>Seventhly, To come to theſe preſent times wherein we live: Is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a man to live a conſcionable and unreprovable life? abſtain from <hi>drunkenneſse, ſwearing, prophaning the Lords day,</hi> ſeparate himſelf from evil company, be zealous for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> admoniſh others that do amiſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without being traduced, calumniated, hated, ſlandered and perſecuted for the ſame? no it is not poſſible: for if a man but walk according to the rule of <hi>Gods word,</hi> he is too preciſe: if he will be more then <hi>almoſt a Christian,</hi> he is curious, phantaſticall, factious, and ſhall be mockt with the <hi>spirit.</hi> What ſhould I ſay? the <hi>world</hi> is grown ſo much knave, that 'tis now a vice to be honeſt. True, bleſſed be <hi>God</hi> and <hi>good Laws,</hi> we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer little but the laſh of evil tongues; but were wicked mens powers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their wills and malice, they would not ſuffer a godly man to live, as I ſhall in due place ſhew you.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, For the time to come: It is like not only to continue, but the laſt remnants of time are ſure to have the moſt of it; becauſe as in them <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ove ſhall wax cold,</hi> Matth. 24.12. ſo as love groweth cold, contention groweth hot.</p>
               <p>More expreſly the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> foretells, that <hi>in the last dayes the times ſhall be perilous,</hi> and that <hi>toward the end of the world, there ſhall be ſcoffers, falſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151476:4"/>accuſers, curſed speakers, fierce, deſpiſers of them that are good; and being fleſhly not having the ſpirit, they ſhall ſpeak evil of the things which they underſtand not: and that many ſhall follow their damnable wayes, whereby the way of truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</hi> And <hi>that as Jannes and Jambres withſtood Moſes, ſo theſe alſo ſhall reſiſt the truth, being men of corrupt mindes, reprobate concerning the faith, being before of old ordained to condemnation,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.1, to 13. 2 Pet. 2 2. and 3.3. Jude 4.10.16, 18, 19. And ſo much of the third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>FOurthly, It would be conſidered, that what you ſuffer is far ſhort of what others have ſuffered before you; for whereas you ſuffer a little tongue-perſecution, your betters and <hi>ſuch as the world was not worthy of,</hi> have <hi>ſuffered cruell mockings, and ſcourgings, bonds, and impriſonments; were ſtoned, ſawn aſunder, tempted, ſlain with the ſword: endured the violence of fire;</hi> were <hi>wract, wandered about in deſarts and mountains, and in dens and caves of the earth, in ſheep-skins and goat-skins, deſtitute, afflicted, tortured and tormented: Not accepting deliverance, that they might obtain a better reſurrection,</hi> Heb. 11.35, to 39. Yea turn over <hi>Eccleſiaſticall History,</hi> and you ſhall finde that ſome of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> were <hi>ſtoned,</hi> ſome <hi>crucified,</hi> ſome <hi>beheaded,</hi> ſome <hi>thruſt thorow with ſpears,</hi> ſome <hi>burnt with fire,</hi> ſome <hi>broyled,</hi> ſome <hi>brained;</hi> with many the like and worſe kindes of death: for we read of no leſſe then <hi>twenty nine ſeverall deaths</hi> they were put unto. But to cleer your ſight, Ile give you ſome particular inſtances of the ſeverall wayes that the beſt of <hi>Gods</hi> people have ſuffered before you.</p>
               <p>Firſt, You ſhall finde, that it hath been the manner of wicked men, out of this enmity, to envy the vertuous and good eſtate of the godly: as <hi>Cain</hi> envied <hi>Abel,</hi> Gen. 4.5. <hi>Saul David,</hi> 1 Sam. 18.28, 29. and thoſe <hi>unbeleeving Jews Paul,</hi> Acts 17.13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To contemn their ſuppoſed mean eſtate, as <hi>Sanballat, Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Gerſhom,</hi> with the reſt of that crue contemned <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> Nehem. 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rabſheke Hezekiah and his people,</hi> 2 King. 18.19, to 36. And the <hi>Epicurean Philoſophers Paul.</hi> Acts 17.18.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, To rejoyce at their ſuppoſed evil eſtate, as the <hi>Princes of the Philiſtins</hi> did at <hi>Sampſons blindneſſe and bondage,</hi> Judg. 16.25. <hi>Peninnah</hi> at <hi>Hannahs barrenneſſe,</hi> eſpecially <hi>when ſhe went up to the houſe of the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.6, 7. And the <hi>Jews</hi> at the <hi>Diſciples</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Church,</hi> when <hi>Herod vexed ſome, and ſlew others,</hi> Acts 12.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, To hate them, as all carnall men hate the <hi>members of Chriſt,</hi> Matth. 10.22. <hi>Ahab Eliah,</hi> 1 King. 22.8. and 18.10. And <hi>Haman Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> Eſth. 3.5, to 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>FIftly, To murmur againſt them, as <hi>Labans ſons</hi> murmured againſt <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> Gen. 31.1. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Numb. 11.1. and 14.2, 3. and the <hi>Labourers in the vineyard, againſt the Maſter of the houſe and their fellowes,</hi> Matth. 20.11, 15.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, To cenſure their actions and miſconſter their intentions, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151476:5"/>
                  <hi>Eliab</hi> did <hi>Davids</hi> zeal for <hi>Gods</hi> glory, in fighting with <hi>Goliah,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.28. and thoſe <hi>wicked ones</hi> his faſting and mourning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.13, to 17. Thus <hi>Jobs friends</hi> cenſured him for an hypocrite, <hi>Job</hi> 4.6, to 11. and the <hi>Jews Chriſtianity</hi> to be <hi>hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Paul the Preacher</hi> of it <hi>a peſtilent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, a mover of ſedition, and maintainer of ſciſme:</hi> yea all the <hi>Diſciples</hi> to be <hi>deceivers,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.8.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, By carrying tales of them unto others, as <hi>Cham</hi> did to his brethren of <hi>Noahs nakedneſse,</hi> Gen. 9.22. <hi>Doeg</hi> to <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleck,</hi> 1 Sam. 22.9, 10. and the <hi>Ziphims,</hi> 1 Sam. 23.19, 20. and 26.1. And thoſe <hi>Libertines</hi> with other ſuborned men againſt <hi>Steven</hi> to the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Prieſts,</hi> Acts 6.8, to 15.</p>
               <p>Eightly, To perſwade and give diveliſh counſell to others like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to perſecute them; as <hi>Balam</hi> to <hi>Balaack</hi> againſt the <hi>Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> when he could not be ſuffered to curſe them <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14. The <hi>Princes and Rulers</hi> to <hi>Zedekiah the King</hi> againſt <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Jer. 38.4. and the <hi>Jews of Theſſalonica</hi> to the <hi>people of Bereah</hi> againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 17.13.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, To ſcoff at them, as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſcoft at <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 21.9. <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheke</hi> at <hi>Hezekiah and his people,</hi> 2 King. 18.27. and the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> at <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 17.18, to 21.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, To nick-name them, as <hi>Ahab</hi> nick-named <hi>Eliah,</hi> 1 King. 18.17. the wicked <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 35.13, 14. <hi>Job</hi> 4.6, to 11. the <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers Jeremiah,</hi> Jer. 37, 15, &amp;c. and the <hi>Jews Paul,</hi> Acts 24.14. and all the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.9.10.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, To revile and rayle on them, as <hi>Goliah</hi> reviled and railed on the <hi>Hoſt of Iſrael</hi> and their <hi>God,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.45. <hi>Shemai</hi> upon <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.7. and likewiſe the <hi>Mighty men,</hi> Pſal. 31.13. and the <hi>Jews</hi> upon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> Acts 13.45.</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, To raiſe ſlanders of them, as thoſe wicked men ſlandered <hi>Naboth,</hi> confirming the ſame with an oath, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. the wicked <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 57.4. and the multitude <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> Matth. 11.18,</p>
               <p>Thirteenthly, To curſe them, as <hi>Goliah</hi> curſed <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.43. and alſo <hi>Shemei,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.7, to 15. the <hi>Heathen Iſrael,</hi> Zach. 8.13. and all wicked men the godly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.44.</p>
               <p>Fourteenthly, To threaten them, as all the <hi>men of Sodom</hi> did <hi>Lot,</hi> Gen. 19.9. <hi>Jehoram Eliſha,</hi> 2 King. 6.31. and as <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſion did the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Acts 9.2.</p>
               <p>Fifteenthly, By ſubtilty to vndermine them in talk, that they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray them; as <hi>Saul</hi> cauſed his ſervants to undermine <hi>David</hi> by flattery to work his confuſion, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.14. and again, <hi>ver.</hi> 21, 25. the <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> and other enemies of the truth <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> ſeeking every way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18, &amp;c. and certain of the <hi>Synagogue Steven,</hi> Acts 6.9, 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>SIxteenthly, By uſing ſcornfull and diſdainfull geſtures to deſpight them; as <hi>Goliah</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 17.42. and alſo thoſe <hi>wicked ones,</hi> Pſal. 22.7, 13. and 35.16. and 109.25. Others againſt <hi>Iob,</hi> Job 16.10.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151476:5"/>The <hi>ſcoffing Idolaters</hi> againſt the <hi>godly</hi> in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time, Iſa. 57.3, 4. and the <hi>Labourers in the Parable</hi> againſt the <hi>Maſter of the Vineyard, and their fellows,</hi> Matth. 20 15.</p>
               <p>Seventeenthly, To withſtand and contrary the doctrine which they are commanded by <hi>God</hi> to deliver: As <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the falſe prophet did <hi>Michai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> doctrine, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.24. the <hi>Prieſts, Prophets</hi> and all the <hi>people Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miahs,</hi> Jer. 26.8, 9. and <hi>Elymas the Sorcerer Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> in their preaching, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.8.</p>
               <p>Eighteenthly, To combine themſelves together and lay divelliſh plots to deſtroy them; as the <hi>new King of Egypt</hi> with his people did againſt the <hi>children of Iſrael,</hi> Exod. 1.9, 10. the <hi>hundreth and twenty Governours,</hi> to work <hi>Daniels</hi> overthrow, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. And <hi>Demetrius with the reſt of the Craftſmen</hi> conſpired the death of <hi>Pauls companions,</hi> Acts 19. and likewiſe <hi>more then forty of the Jews, which bound themſelves by a curſe, not to eat nor drink till they had killed Paul;</hi> in which conſpiracy the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> were likewiſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.12, 13, 14.</p>
               <p>Nineteenthly, To impriſon them, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Michaiah,</hi> 1 King. 22.27. the malicious <hi>Prieſts Ieremiah,</hi> Jer. 36.5. and all wicked men the godly, when it is in their power, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.12. as they ſerved <hi>John Baptiſt, Peter, Paul</hi> and many other of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.18. and 12.4. and 4.3. and 22.25. and 28.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.</p>
               <p>Twentieth, To ſtrike them, as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the falſe Prophet ſtrook <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah,</hi> 1 King. 22.24, <hi>Paſhur Ieremiah,</hi> Jer. 20.2. and the <hi>Princes</hi> alſo, <hi>chap.</hi> 37.15. and <hi>Ananias</hi> the High Prieſt <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 23.2. as alſo the <hi>Jews,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.23, 24, 25.</p>
               <p>Twenty one, To hurt and maim them, as the whole <hi>Congregation of the children of Iſrael</hi> would have ſerved thoſe <hi>true hearted spies,</hi> for ſpeaking well of the <hi>Land of Canaan,</hi> had not <hi>the glory of the Lord appeared in the Tabernacle of the Congregation,</hi> Numb. 14.10. the <hi>Philiſtims Sampſon,</hi> Judg. 16.21. and the <hi>Jews of Antiochia and Iconium Paul,</hi> Acts 14.19.</p>
               <p>Twenty two and laſtly, To ſlay them, as <hi>Doeg</hi> ſlew <hi>Ahimeleck and the reſt of the Prieſts,</hi> 1 Sam. 22, 29. <hi>Iezabell</hi> all the <hi>Prophets</hi> of the Lord ſhe could finde, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the Prophets, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod all the male-children that were in Bethlehem and all the coaſts thereof, that he might make ſure work with Chriſt,</hi> Matth. 2.16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>NOw to ſpeak nothing in this place of the diverſity of deaths and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that millions of <hi>Martyrs</hi> have ſuffered <hi>for profeſsing of Chriſts Name</hi> and keeping of a good conſcience, though their ſufferings were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, either to what their ſins had deſerved, or to what their <hi>Saviour</hi> had done and ſuffered for them; for he endured many a little death all his life for our ſakes, and at length that painfull, ſhamefull and curſed <hi>death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the croſse:</hi> yea he ſuffered every one of theſe two and twenty wayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ementioned, and that from his own countrymen and kinsfolks, yea of the <hi>Chief Prieſts, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were <hi>teachers and expounders of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151476:6"/>the Law, and which ſate in Moſes chair.</hi> For he was <hi>envied,</hi> Matth. 26.15. <hi>Contemned,</hi> Matth. 12.24. and 13.55. <hi>Rejoyced at</hi> in his miſery and diſtreſſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.29. <hi>Hated,</hi> Joh. 7.7. <hi>Murmured against,</hi> Luk. 15.2. <hi>Had his actions and intentions miſconſtrued,</hi> Matth. 11.19. Had <hi>tales carryed of him,</hi> Matth. 12.14. and diveliſh <hi>counſel given</hi> againſt him, Matth. 27.20. was <hi>ſcoffed at,</hi> Matth. 27.42. <hi>Nick-named,</hi> Matth. 13.55. <hi>Railed on,</hi> Luk. 23.39. <hi>Slandered,</hi> Matth. 28.13. <hi>Curſed,</hi> Gal. 3.13. <hi>Threatned,</hi> Joh. 11.53. <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined</hi> in talk that they might accuſe him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.15. They uſed <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainfull gestures</hi> before him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.29, 39. <hi>Withſtood him in his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and contraried his doctrine, <hi>Luk</hi> 5.21. Matth. 9.34. <hi>Combined together</hi> and laid divelliſh plots to deſtroy him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.14. Took him <hi>priſoner,</hi> Matth. 26.57. <hi>Smote him,</hi> Luk. 22.64. <hi>Hurt and wounded him,</hi> Matth. 27.29. Joh. 19.34. And laſtly they <hi>put him to death,</hi> Matth. 27.35. And why all this? not for any evil they found in him; for their own words are, <hi>He hath done all things well,</hi> Mark. 7.37. He hath done, ſuch was his power: all things, ſuch was his wiſdom: well, ſuch was his goodneſſe: and yet crucified and every way abuſed he muſt be. But it was for his zeal, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and holineſſe, and becauſe his life and practice was clean contrary to theirs; his doctrine too powerfull and pure for ſuch carnall hearts to imbrace or endure. Now caſt up thy Receits, and compare them with thy deſervings; look upon thy deliverance from the <hi>fire of hell:</hi> Yea look but upon thy ſufferings ſingle, and thou ſhalt finde them nothing, to what thy <hi>fellow Saints</hi> and <hi>Chriſt thy elder brother</hi> hath ſuffered before thee. At a <hi>Lyons den,</hi> or a <hi>fiery furnace</hi> not to turn tayl, were ſomething worthy a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> Yea compare thine own eſtate with thine enemies, and thou ſhalt ſee yet greater cauſe to be not only patient but thankfull. For if theſe ſcoffs and flouts of men like thy ſelf are ſo grievous to thee, how will thine and <hi>Gods</hi> enemies indure thoſe <hi>mocks and flouts of the divels in hell?</hi> how will they indure <hi>that devouring fire, that everlaſting burning,</hi> Iſa. 33.14. Pſal 68.21. And the way not to repine at thoſe above us, is to look at thoſe below us. But leaving the application untill the concluſion,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>FIftly, Conſider but ſeriouſly, who they are, that hate, ſcoff and jeer you and that have perſecuted the Saints before you, and mockt at holineſſe and this may ſerve exceedingly to ſupport you againſt whatever you ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hear or feel from them. As firſt, what is their <hi>Character in the Scripture</hi> are they not ſuch as theſe? A company of hypocrites, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call mockers,</hi> ver. 16. a crue of drunkards, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. <hi>I am a ſong of the dru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kards,</hi> ver. 12. a ſort of vicious perſons, following their luſts, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>There ſhall come mockers, walking after their own luſts.</hi> A company of <hi>abje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> perſons,</hi> Pſal. 35.15. like thoſe <hi>enemies,</hi> Acts 17. <hi>Lewd fellowes of the baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſort,</hi> ver. 5. <hi>A rout of prophane, godleſs, irreligious atheiſts and ignorant foo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> that do no more know the power, then <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>heathens</hi> know the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of godlineſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1, to 6. And it is a ſhrewd ſuſpition, that he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is <hi>a mocker</hi> is <hi>an atheiſt:</hi> It well becomes him to mock at <hi>Religion,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151476:6"/>denies a <hi>God:</hi> and it is evident enough that he denies a <hi>God,</hi> that mocks at godlineſſe. But ſecondly, <hi>Experience</hi> ſufficiently acquaints us what they are, and the <hi>examples</hi> before rehearſed; for ſuch as <hi>Cain,</hi> and the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and <hi>Haman,</hi> and <hi>Eliab,</hi> and <hi>Goliah,</hi> and <hi>Michal,</hi> and <hi>Doeg,</hi> and <hi>Shemy,</hi> and <hi>Rabſheke,</hi> and <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Iezabel,</hi> and <hi>Tobia,</hi> and <hi>Sanballat,</hi> and <hi>Paſhur,</hi> and <hi>Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ekiah,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> and <hi>Iudas:</hi> and St <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his converſion, and <hi>Ananias the High Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Dometrius the ſilver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith,</hi> and <hi>Alexander the copper ſmith,</hi> and <hi>Elimas the Sorcerer:</hi> ſuch as theſe I ſay are the men, who amongſt us do the like things that they did. And will any wiſe man ſtumble at Religion for ſuch mens ſcoffs and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es? what better can be expected from them? What ſaid the <hi>Orator</hi> to <hi>Saluſt?</hi> It cannot be, but he that lives thy life ſhould ſpeak thy language: yea a man would chooſe his Religion by ſuch mens enmity, and it is a great honour to Religion that it hath ſuch adverſaries. For as the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians</hi> uſed to ſay when <hi>Nero</hi> perſecuted them; they that know him muſt needs think it ſome great good which <hi>Nero</hi> ſo hated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; ſo every wiſe man will love Religion the better, and take it for a great honour to the Saints, that <hi>hypocrites, drunkards, vitious followers of their luſts, baſe and lewd fellowes, godleſs atheists, and blind ſenſualiſts</hi> are her ſcoffing adverſaries: And ſcarce do I know a better argument to perſwade to love and embrace it, then that ſuch men hate and deride it: neither can it be the true Religion, which is not every where thus ſpoken againſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.22. But</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>SIxtly and laſtly, Obſerve but the reaſons why they do it; and this will notably confirm and ſtrengthen you againſt their ſcoffs and ſcorns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Convert.</hi> Have they any reaſon for their ſo doing?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miniſter.</hi> Not properly: For as the Prophet very often complains, <hi>they are mine enemies without a cauſe,</hi> and <hi>they hate me without a cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.7. and 69.4. though they pretended many cauſes. So they have no juſt cauſe nor reaſon to hate, cenſure and ſlander us as they do; for no evil deed can have a good reaſon: yet they do it not without many by-reaſons and ſelf ends. As</p>
               <p>Firſt, Their ignorance is a main cauſe of it, naturall men in heavenly things, reſemble <hi>ſhell-fiſh,</hi> that have no ſmell; or the <hi>Camelion,</hi> that hath no taſt, at leaſt they ſee no more then the <hi>bark</hi> or <hi>outſide</hi> of ſpirituall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 6.16. And the fleſh (Satans ready inſtrument) will be ever ſuggeſting to them ſtrange ſurmiſes touching what the religious ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay or do. As is evident by what is recorded of <hi>Michol,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.16. of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> Joh. 3.4. of <hi>Feſtus,</hi> Acts 26.24. and laſtly of <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his converſion, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. who was no ſooner enlightned with the ſaving knowledge of the truth, but he preacht that faith which before he condemned and perſecuted.</p>
               <p>And for teſtimonies to confirm it theſe are pregnant, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.21. and 16.2, 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.23. and 22.29. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.42. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p>Though experience may ſave that labour: for how ſeverely will theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151476:7"/>ignorant perſons cenſure and ſlander not only things indifferent, but the moſt approved good duties; while they will patiently paſſe by the moſt hainous crimes: an infallible ſign of a man not born anew.</p>
               <p>And ſtill the more ſottiſh the more cenſorious; for where is <hi>leaſt brain,</hi> there is <hi>moſt tongue</hi> and lowdeſt. And as ignorance gives diſparagement a lowder tongue then knowledge does, ſo alwayes they that <hi>know leaſt</hi> will <hi>cenſure moſt</hi> and moſt deeply. It is from the <hi>weakest judgements</hi> that the <hi>heavieſt judgement</hi> comes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Sometimes on the other ſide, they will cenſure and ſlander them in policie: that while the ſtanders by are taken up with jeering at our ſuppoſed ſimplicity, they may not minde their paſt and intended reall villany. Therein imitating a <hi>thief,</hi> who being purſued in a croud, will be forwardeſt in <hi>crying ſtop thief,</hi> that ſo he may neither be attached nor ſuſpected: The caſe of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> 2 King. 11.14.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Another reaſon may be this; Who ſo hath any thing fixed, either in their perſons or conditions which cauſeth contempt, As they are commonly very bold, ſo they have a kinde of ſpur in them, and are moſt induſtriouſly ſtirred up to watch, obſerve and cenſure the weakneſſes of others; that ſo they may have ſomewhat again to repay. See the caſe of <hi>Shemei</hi> touching <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.7. of the <hi>High Prieſts, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> touching our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Luk. 5.21. Matth. 9.3, 34. and 12.1, 2. and 16.17. and 21.2, 14, 15, 16, 24, 45, 46. and 22.15, 16, 17. and 27.41, 42. And laſtly of <hi>Iudas</hi> touching <hi>Mary,</hi> Joh. 12.4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>FOurthly In ſuch as are not regenerate, nor were ever diſciplin'd in the ſchool of <hi>Christ.</hi> The ignobleneſſe of their diſpoſitions and breeding, may be a ſufficient ground: For baſeneſſe, what it cannot attain to, it will vilicate and deprave. As no wonder if a Carter cenſure a Scholler, or a Clown a Courtier; ſo none can think it ſtrange that brutiſh ſenſualiſts, ſhould cenſure the Saints for <hi>ſullen, ſhallow, cenſorious, proud, diſſembling,</hi> &amp;c. That they ſhould miſtake the way to <hi>Heaven</hi> for the moſt melancholy walk, when all that are born of <hi>God,</hi> and taught by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> know them the moſt <hi>merry, wiſe, charitable, humble</hi> and <hi>plain dealing</hi> people.</p>
               <p>Indeed time and experience will alter their judgements be they never ſo brutiſh and baſe: as it univerſally fared with the <hi>old world,</hi> Gen. 6. and 7. chapters, who for one hundred and twenty years together, harboured ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny baſe thoughts of <hi>Noah:</hi> thinking him half mad, to beſtow ſo much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and coſt in building ſo vaſt a veſſel as the Ark was: but in proceſſe of time, when they ſtood upon the tops of the mountains, expecting within a minute to be drowned in thoſe waters: they beheld him ſecure to their greater vexation: and acknowledged themſelves ſtark mad for not timely beleeving him.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, Guiltineſſe is another main reaſon: for commonly ſuſpition pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a ſelf-defect: and a bad conſtruction from a bad minde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deceit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull, over will miſtruſtfull be: But no miſtruſt, is found in honeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151476:7"/>
               <p> Naturall men, moſtly meaſure others by their own buſhel; and ſo form their opinions and cenſures of us according to the mold of wickedneſſe that is in their own hearts: and doing all their own good in hipocriſie, they cannot think us better then themſelves.</p>
               <p>And yet it is a rule which ſeldom fails: That as <hi>Cham</hi> was worſe then <hi>Noah</hi> whom he derided: and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> worſe then <hi>Iſaac</hi> whom he mocked: and <hi>Saul</hi> worſe then <hi>David</hi> whom he perſecuted: and <hi>Iezabel</hi> worſe then <hi>Naboth</hi> whom ſhe defamed and murthered: and <hi>Herod</hi> worſe then <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> whom he beheaded. So they which are wont to cenſure and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der others, have greater faults themſelves, and cauſe to be cenſured and condemned of others: which faults they cannot tell how to cover, but by diſgracing of others. And the cenſured in Scripture, are alwayes more precious in Gods ſight then the cenſurer: as in the <hi>Phariſee</hi> and <hi>Publican,</hi> Luk. 18. and in thoſe <hi>Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 28.3, 4.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, Pride is no ſmall cauſe: for a proud man is wont to admire his own actions, but to abate the valu, and derogate from the eſteem of others; every whit as baſely to vilifie other mens doings, as he over highly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth his own. <hi>I</hi> (ſaith the proud <hi>Phariſee</hi>) <hi>am not as this Publican,</hi> Luk. 18.11. Neither was he if you mark it: for the <hi>Publican</hi> condemning himſelf was juſtified and ſaved: he juſtifying himſelf was everlaſtingly condemned.</p>
               <p>Again, They know their glory and credit with the world, is greatly eclipſed by ſuch as excell in vertue: Their vicious lives are plainly repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and their perſons moſt grievouſly ſhamed by the holy converſation of good men. And this makes them ſmut the face that is fairer: blemiſh honeſt mens fame by their cenſuring and aſperſions; that they may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate their own ſhame with others diſcredit; like <hi>Potiphars wife,</hi> they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend we are guilty, that themſelves may be taken for innocent.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Another cauſe is prejudice or miſpriſion; for this like a painted pair of <hi>Spectacles,</hi> caſteth a falſe colour upon the beſt actions. As we ſee in <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezabel,</hi> touching <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Micaiah.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <p>EIghtly, They ſuppoſe we are not as we ſeem, <hi>ergo</hi> we are Puritants, Hypocrits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A reaſon of great force with States men and Polititians: <hi>Herod</hi> thinks <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes to dethrone him; therefore to make ſure work, ke murthers all the males in <hi>Bethlem. Cambyſes</hi> dreames overnight, that his brother ſhould be King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> therefore he puts him to death the next morning. <hi>Saul</hi> ſuppoſes <hi>David</hi> a traytor, therefore <hi>know ye not that the ſonne of Ieſſe hath conspired againſt me?</hi> But it were as good an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to reaſon thus: All the Apoſtles were impoſters, and the Goſpel it ſelf a fable; for ſo thought the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees.</hi> A man ſhall do <hi>God good ſervice, in perſecuting of his faithfull ſervants;</hi> for ſo thought the <hi>Prelates</hi> (as themſelves have confeſt upon their examination.) Or laſtly, there is no <hi>God,</hi> for ſo <hi>the fool hath ſaid in his heart,</hi> Pſal. 14.1. and 53.1.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, They envy the godly, either firſt, becauſe they do better, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151476:8"/>
                  <hi>Cain</hi> did <hi>Abel;</hi> or ſecondly, becauſe they fare better, as <hi>Eſau</hi> did <hi>Iacob:</hi> or thirdly, becauſe they are better eſteemed, as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>David.</hi> And this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> another cauſe, for ill will never ſpeaks well; and envy is <hi>ſick</hi> if her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour be <hi>well.</hi> The ones ſucceſſe is the others vexation, the envious <hi>emulate</hi> what they cannot <hi>imitate.</hi> Whence ariſes all their cenſuring and miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing their perſons, actions and intentions. For whom they cannot reach by <hi>imitation,</hi> they will endeavour to do by <hi>detraction:</hi> and becauſe they cannot <hi>ſeduce us,</hi> they will if they can <hi>traduce us;</hi> if we will not partake with them in their <hi>ſins,</hi> we ſhall in their <hi>ſhame;</hi> if <hi>Ioſeph</hi> will not be lewd with his miſtreſs, he ſhall be thought as guilty, and ſuffer as much as if he were.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, Sometimes they cenſure and ſlander us out of ſelf-love; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they may gain, or at leaſt not loſe of their honours, pleaſures, profits: <hi>Sauls</hi> flatterers will ſooth him up in his evil ſurmiſes againſt <hi>David;</hi> ſaying The ſonne of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> hath conſpired againſt thee; that they may have <hi>fields</hi> and <hi>Vineyards</hi> given them; be made <hi>Captains over thouſands,</hi> and <hi>Captains over hundreds.</hi> And this tempted <hi>Balaam</hi> againſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, even to <hi>curſe</hi> where he ſhould <hi>bleſse:</hi> he ſaw how his curſing and curſed counſel might pleaſe <hi>Balack,</hi> and bleſſe himſelf with a gainfull and gallant promotion. And the like in <hi>Demetrius,</hi> for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſubſtracts from <hi>Demetrius</hi> his profit, ſo <hi>Demetrius</hi> detracts from <hi>Pauls</hi> credit.</p>
               <p>Which was many a mans caſe within theſe few years: for ſome have climed up to preferment by envaying againſt the Puritans: and others been ruined and diſgraced by preaching againſt the Prelates.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, By depraving all good men themſelves, (though ſwearers, drunkards, whoremongers,) ſhall be judged indifferent honeſt men: for were all the world ugly, deformity would be no monſter. Yea, a baſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may come to preferment, if none be thought better then himſelf. He that hath but one eye, may be King amongſt the blinde. Whereupon, to have themſelves thought as good as any other, they will not have any thought good that dwells near them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>TWelfthly, Their paſſions and affections make them ſo exceeding partiall, that they will more deeply cenſure our fearing of God, then their own blaſpheming him; and hold it a more hainous crime for us to be ſober, then for themſelves to be drunk.</p>
               <p>You may think it a big word for want of acquaintance with ſuch: But Drunkards and Swearers know I ſpeak truth. And I the more confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeve my own ears, when I conſider the <hi>Sodomites</hi> quarrell with <hi>Lot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and many the like in Scripture. As how did the paſſion of Anger, rob <hi>Haman</hi> of his reaſon, when he thought <hi>Mordecais</hi> not bowing the knee to him, a more hainous offence, then his own murthering of thouſands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And <hi>Jezabels</hi> who thought it a greater ſin in <hi>Eliah</hi> to kill <hi>Baals Prieſts</hi> then in her ſelf, to ſlay all <hi>the Prophets if the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But no wonder, for as the Eye only looks to things without. And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they that are vertiginous think all things turn round, all erre; when the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151476:8"/>errour is only in their own brains: ſo fares it with ſenſuall men, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by paſſion, and given up to their luſts. They put their own faults in that part of the Wallet which is behinde them; but ours, in the other part or end which is before them. Indeed ſelf-examination would make their judgements more charitable.</p>
               <p>Thirteenthly, The perſons cenſuring and cenſured, are as contrary in their natures as are <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell, Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſſe, God</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> the one being <hi>Satans ſeed,</hi> and born after the <hi>Fleſh:</hi> the other being <hi>Chriſts members,</hi> and born after the ſpirit, <hi>John</hi> 3.8. to 15. And this makes the one hate, what the other loves. <hi>A wicked man</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, is abomination to the just, and he that is upright in his way, is abomination to the wicked.</hi> Prov. 29.27. even our waies, which God commands us to walk in, as well as our perſons, are abomination to them.</p>
               <p>Yea, we ſee by experience, that there is a curſed Zeal in theſe men to malign the good Zeal of all men. And that uſually they are pleaſed beſt with that which angers God moſt: No marvell then if they cenſure and ſlander ſuch as he lovesbeſt.</p>
               <p>Fourteenthly, They delight in cenſuring and ſlandering us: becauſe Satan (who is their God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. and their Prince, <hi>Job.</hi> 14.30. <hi>and works in them his pleaſure,</hi> Eph. 2.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.) is ever prompting them thereunto, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.10. For it is Satan that ſpeaks in and by them, as once he did by the Serpent: It is his minde in their mouth, his heart in their lips, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.23.</p>
               <p>And they being his Sons, Servants and Subjects, thirſt to do him what honour and ſervice they can. Nor can they pleaſure him more, it being the hopefulleſt way to diſcourage men in the way to heaven, quench the good motions of Gods ſpirit, kill the buds and beginnings of grace, draw them back to the world, and ſo by conſequence damn their ſouls, that can be, to ſee that whatſoever they do or ſpeak; baſe conſtructions are made thereof. Whereas if they medled not with repentance, nor troubled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about religion: the world nor the devil would not meddle with them, nor once trouble or moleſt them.</p>
               <p>Beſides their cenſures, and falſe aſperſions, cauſe jealouſies where there are none, encreaſeth thoſe thot are, mightily diſables ſome from diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth, and much hinders others from beleeving it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <p>FIfteenthly, <hi>Zoylus</hi>-like they cenſure, and ſpeak evill of us: becauſe they cannot otherwiſe hurt us.</p>
               <p>They dare not ſmite us on the mouth as the High-Prieſt ſerved <hi>Paul:</hi> therefore they ſmite us with the mouth: as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the falſe Prophet ſerved <hi>Michaiah:</hi> which is as bad or worſe. For deal they not with the godly, as the daughters of <hi>Heth</hi> did by <hi>Rebecca,</hi> Gen. 27. who made her weary of her life, and forced her to cry out in the bitterneſſe of her ſoul, <hi>What availeth it me to live:</hi> verſ. 46. In which they imitate their Father the devil: who when his hands are bound, <hi>vomits out a floud of reproaches with his tongue.</hi> Rev. 12.15.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151476:9"/>
               <p> I confeſſe they were wont, <hi>Maximinus</hi> like, to ſpeak evil of us; that ſo they might perſecute us with the more ſhew of reaſon: accuſe us to the Prelats, as the Jews did <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Agrippa:</hi> charging us with many things, but proving nothing, neither could they well undo us, if firſt they did not falſely accuſe us: as it fared with <hi>Iezabel</hi> touching <hi>Naboth,</hi> and the wife of <hi>Potiphar</hi> touching <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though a little information would ſerve: for malice regards not how true any accuſation is, but how ſpitefull. And theſe prelats, were ſo far from diſcerning or deſiring to diſcern truth from ſlander, that to the grief of many good hearts; no muſick could be ſo ſweet to their ears, as to hear well of themſelves, ill of the religious. And they were as ready to yeeld their aid as the other to ask it; being men of the High-Prieſts humour; who ſeeing none offer themſelves ſet on work certain vile perſons, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe Chriſt of hainous evils: that ſo they might crucifie him by a Law: Yea our reverend Biſhops and their bandogs dealt with a poor Miniſter or Chriſtian, juſt as the ſouldiers did by our Saviour: Firſt blinde him, then ſtrike him, and laſt ask him, <hi>who was it that ſmote thee?</hi> and he might anſwer the beſt of the three; It was thou O mine Enemy, thou waſt an an <hi>Achitophel</hi> in the one, a <hi>Doeg</hi> in the other, a <hi>Belial</hi> in both.</p>
               <p>Sixteenthly, They cenſure, and in cenſuring ſlander us: that they may incite and ſtir up others to do the like: Reſembling thoſe ancient enemies of the Goſpel, who clad the Martyrs in the skins of wilde beaſts: to animate the dogs to tear them.</p>
               <p>It is the nature of ignorant and ill-bred people, who <hi>walk after the fleſh in the luſt of uncleanneſſe,</hi> whom S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>bruit beaſts, led with ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, and made to be taken and deſtroyed, to speak evil of the things which they underſtand not,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.12. And what one doth is a Law to the reſt. As if one in their company but mentions the word Puritan, or tells them how ſcrupulous and preciſe ſuch an one is: all the reſt will ſtrive who ſhall be forwardeſt in ſpitting out his ſpleen againſt all the godly. As what a number of ſharp and deadly Arrows will each of them ſhoot; both at the good and goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>Nor are they ſo ſatisfied: but every one runs away with the cry: and barks out the term againſt every honeſt man he meets, whence it is that we are cenſured, and laught to ſcorn by the greateſt number: that we are made the common Butt of every ones malice, and the ſubject of all their diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Which yet is no diſparagement to us: for theſe are a generation of men; that (for matter of religion) can ſcarcely <hi>diſcern between their right hand and their left:</hi> as it fared with thoſe ſixſcore thouſand <hi>Ninevites,</hi> Jon. 4.11. I might heap up inſtances to prove how ſtrongly and ſtrangely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample prevails, to the committing of evil with ignorant perſons, who are Ceſterns to ſin, Sives to grace. As in the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> Gen. 19.4. to 12. In <hi>Korah and his</hi> 150. <hi>followers:</hi> In <hi>Demetrius and his fellows,</hi> Acts 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is too well known, how many do cenſure and blaſpheme the Godly, becauſe they hear others do ſo.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151476:9"/>
               <p> Nor is it the common peoples caſe alone: who enquire no farther but beleeve at firſt: for then I ſhould no whit wonder. But even our grave Biſhops and Fathers of the Church did not long ſince go thus by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and perſecute the conſcionable, becauſe drunkards and deboiſhed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did ſo: cenſuring them in their <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> and other Courts Eccleſiaſticall; as the other did on their Ale-benches.</p>
               <p>It may ſeem above beleef, and yet it was ſo, only thoſe barking Currs did theſe great Maſtifs wake: Whom we may liken to noyſome Flies, which ſting while they live, and ſtink when they are dead; though bleſſed be God we are now rid of them.</p>
               <p>I need not tell you how many of their Lordſhips and their Creatures have come to their great preferments by being bitter Malignants againſt the beſt men: for no knowing man can thereof be ignorant.</p>
               <p>Thus I migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> go on in giving you other reaſons of their cenſuring and ſlandering us; as one in regard of Satan, who loſeth ſo many of his Subjects or Captives as turn beleevers: for every repentant ſinner is as a priſoner broke looſe from his chains of darkneſſe,</p>
               <p>And another in regard of the World, which loſeth a limb or member: When a convert will no longer accompany them in their wicked cuſtoms. And ſhew you, that it fares with all beleevers as it did with <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſo long as he joyned with the <hi>High-Priests</hi> and <hi>Elders to make havock of the Church</hi> was no whit moleſted by them; but when he became a convert and preached in the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> none ſo hated and perſecuted as he.</p>
               <p>I might alſo make it appear, that <hi>atheiſme</hi> or <hi>unbelief</hi> is another cauſe, <hi>ſpeaking of truth</hi> another, <hi>breaking off ſociety with them</hi> another, <hi>the ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine preaching of ſome Miniſters</hi> another, <hi>the ſcandalous lives of ſome profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors</hi> another, <hi>flocking after Sermons</hi> another, as they make them: but theſe I'le paſſe, and give you but one more, with which I will conclude this diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <p>THe main and moſt materiall cauſe why wicked men ſo mortally hate the godly, and which breeds ſo many quarrels, is the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of their natures, as I briefly hinted in the thirteenth reaſon; being as contrary one to the other as are <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>devil,</hi> the one being the <hi>children of God, and partaking of the divine nature,</hi> as <hi>being one with the Father and the Son,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.18. Gal. 3.26. Joh. 1.12. &amp; 17.14, 21, 22. 2 Pet. 1.4. being <hi>like God in holineſſe,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.15. <hi>Bretheren of, and heirs annexed with Christ,</hi> Rom. 8.17, 29. <hi>Members of his body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.27. <hi>Bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh,</hi> Eph. 5.30. <hi>having his spirit dwelling in them,</hi> Rom. 8.9, 16. and being <hi>Temples of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.19. Jam. 1.18. Joh. 1.13. &amp; 3.5, 8. 1 Joh. 3.9.</p>
               <p>And the other being the <hi>ſeed of the ſerpent and children of the devil;</hi> and ſo partake of his nature, as is plain by 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8.10, 12, 14. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.70. &amp; 8.44. Matth. 13.38, 39. 2 Cor. 4.4. 2 Tim. 2.26. Gen. 3.15. &amp; 5.3. Epheſ. 2.2, &amp;c. Which being ſo, how is it poſſible they ſhould ever agree; although <hi>God</hi> had not proclaimed an enmity between them? For there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151476:10"/>can be no amity where there is no ſimpathy; no reconciling of the <hi>wolfe</hi> and the <hi>lambe,</hi> the <hi>winds</hi> and the <hi>ſea;</hi> No neighbourhood, no alliance, no conjunction, is able to make the curſed <hi>ſeed of the ſerpent,</hi> and the bleſſed <hi>ſeed of the woman</hi> ever agree. For <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water, light</hi> and <hi>darkneſse, Heaven</hi> and <hi>hell</hi> are not more contrary.</p>
               <p>One <hi>bloud,</hi> one <hi>belly,</hi> one <hi>houſe,</hi> one <hi>education,</hi> could never make <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> accord, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> at one. Yea though they be <hi>man</hi> and <hi>wife, parent</hi> and <hi>childe,</hi> yet if they be not like they will not like. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15. And indeed what is the corporall ſimpathy, to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall antipathy? Can there be ſuch a parity between the <hi>parent</hi> and the <hi>childe,</hi> the <hi>husband</hi> and the <hi>wife,</hi> as there is a diſparity between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Satan?</hi> no certainly.</p>
               <p>A wicked man can agree with all that are wicked, be they <hi>Papists,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Atheiſts; Prophane</hi> or <hi>Civill</hi> men: for all theſe agree with him in blindeneſſe and darkneſſe: but with ſincere <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and practiſers of piety he can never agree; the religious ſhall be ſure of oppoſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their light is contrary to his darkneſſe, grace in the one is a ſecret diſgrace to the other.</p>
               <p>Yea let wicked men be at never ſo much ods one with another, yet they will concur and joyn againſt the godly. The <hi>Libertines, Cirenians, Alexandrians, Celicians</hi> and <hi>Aſians,</hi> differ they never ſo much, will join in diſpute againſt <hi>Steven,</hi> Act. 6.9. The <hi>Saduces, Phariſes</hi> and <hi>Herodians,</hi> were ſectaries of divers and adverſe factions, all differing one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet all join together againſt our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Matth. 22. <hi>Herod</hi> neither loved the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor the <hi>Jews Herod,</hi> yet both are agreed to vex the Church. Yea <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> two enemies will agree ſo it be againſt <hi>Chriſt:</hi> they will fall in one with another, to fall out with <hi>God.</hi> Nature will give a man leave to be any thing ſave a ſound <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and agree with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, be their opinions never ſo contrary; provided they agree in the main, are all ſeed of the ſame ſerpent: but let the naturall man meet with one that is ſpirituall, they agree like <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>cold,</hi> if the one ſtayes the other flies; or if both ſtay, they agree like two <hi>poiſons</hi> in one <hi>ſtomach,</hi> the one being ever ſick of the other be they never ſo neer allied. As how many a <hi>wife</hi> is ſo much the more hated, becauſe a zealous wife? how many a <hi>childe</hi> leſſe beloved, becauſe a religious childe? how many a <hi>ſervant</hi> leſſe reſpected, becauſe a godly ſervant? And no marvell, for though they dwell in the ſame <hi>houſe,</hi> yet they belong to two ſeverall <hi>Kingdoms:</hi> and albeit they both remain upon <hi>earth,</hi> yet they are governed by two ſeverall <hi>Laws,</hi> the ones <hi>Burguſhip</hi> being in <hi>heaven,</hi> Phil. 3.20. and the other being a <hi>denizon</hi> belonging to <hi>hell;</hi> as <hi>Iriſh men</hi> are dwellers in <hi>Ircland,</hi> but <hi>doni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and governed by the <hi>Statutes</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>NOr is this of theirs an ordinary <hi>hatred,</hi> but the <hi>moſt bitter, exorbitant unlimited</hi> and <hi>implacable</hi> of all others. No ſuch concord, no ſuch diſcord, ſaith one of the Learned, as that which proceeds from Religion.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151476:10"/>My name, ſayes <hi>Luther,</hi> is more odious to them, then any <hi>thiefe</hi> or <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer;</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was more deteſtable to the <hi>Jews,</hi> then <hi>Barabas.</hi> And it was evident enough; for the <hi>Pope</hi> was ſo buſie and hot againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> that he neglected to look to all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> againſt the <hi>Turk:</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that he would eaſier diſgeſt <hi>Mahometiſme</hi> then <hi>Lutheraniſme.</hi> The caſe of two many in our daies, in oppoſing the <hi>reformation. Behold,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, mine enemies, for they are many; and they hate me with a cruell hatred,</hi> Pſal. 25.19. yea ſo cruell, that it makes their <hi>teeth gnaſh,</hi> and their <hi>hearts burſt</hi> again, as it fared with thoſe that ſtoned <hi>Steven,</hi> Acts 7.54. This made the truths adverſaries, give S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul ſtripes above meaſure,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.23. And the <hi>Heathen Emperours,</hi> to deviſe ſuch cruell tortures, for all thoſe that but profeſt themſelve; <hi>Christians.</hi> This made <hi>Ahab</hi> ſo hate <hi>Eliah,</hi> that <hi>there was not one Kingdom or Nation, where he had not ſent to take away his life,</hi> 1 King. 18.10. And this made the <hi>Papiſts</hi> dig many of our choice <hi>Miniſters</hi> out of their <hi>graves,</hi> that they might the better curſe them, with <hi>bell, bock</hi> and <hi>candle.</hi> Yea ask from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> from one <hi>Pole</hi> to the other; ſearch all records under <hi>Heaven,</hi> if ever there was the like, of the intended <hi>Powder plot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither does this hatred extend it ſelf to this or that perſon alone, but to the whole generation of the godly; as is well expreſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>Come let us cut them off from being a Nation, and let the Name of Iſrael be no more in remembrance,</hi> ver. 4, 12. And the like we ſee in <hi>Haman,</hi> whoſe hatred to <hi>Mordecai</hi> was ſo deadly, that he thought it too little to lay hands on him only, except he deſtroyed all the <hi>Jews</hi> his people, that were throughout the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> Eſth. 3.5, 6. For the effecting whereof he offered <hi>ten thouſand tallents of ſilver into the Kings treaſury,</hi> ver. 9, 13. And of his minde was <hi>Herodias,</hi> who preferred the head of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> before <hi>the half of Herods Kingdom.</hi> And ſuch another was cruell <hi>Arundale Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Canterbury,</hi> who ſwore he would not leave a ſlip of profeſſors in this Land.</p>
               <p>And the world is no changeling, for this age hath but too many ſuch <hi>Hamans</hi> and <hi>Arundales,</hi> who ſo hate the children of <hi>God,</hi> that they wiſh as <hi>Caligula</hi> once did of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that they had all but one neck, that ſo they might cut it off at a blow, were it in their power. As why are not our <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> turned into <hi>ſhambles?</hi> and our <hi>Beds</hi> made to ſwim with our <hi>blouds?</hi> but that the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath croſſed the confederacy of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack,</hi> and their wickedneſſe doth not proſper. For their ſtudies are the plots of our ruine; and the beſt they intend, is the deſtruction and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of <hi>Religion,</hi> or the <hi>religious,</hi> or both, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.2. Yea their enmity and hatred is ſo virulent and bitter, that were their power anſwerable to their wils and malice, the <hi>brother</hi> would betray the <hi>brother</hi> to death, the <hi>father</hi> the <hi>ſonne,</hi> and the <hi>children</hi> would riſe up againſt their <hi>parents,</hi> and cauſe them to die; the <hi>kinſman</hi> againſt the <hi>kinſman,</hi> and the <hi>friend</hi> againſt the <hi>friend;</hi> only for profeſſing <hi>Chriſts Name</hi> and being religious, as himſelf affirms, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.34, 35, 36. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.16, 17. Neither is it ſtrange, for this was one of the ends of <hi>Chriſts</hi> coming into the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151476:11"/>world, as appears <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.34, 35. where himſelf ſaith, <hi>Think not that I am come to ſend peace but the ſword:</hi> meaning between the <hi>ſeed of the ſerpent,</hi> and the <hi>ſeed of the woman: for I am come to ſet a man at variance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his father, the daughter in law angainst the mother in law, and a mans ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall be they of his own houſhold,</hi> Luk. 12.51, 52, 53.</p>
               <p>Neither want we preſidents of this: For by whom was upright <hi>Abel</hi> perſecuted and ſlaine, but by his own brother <hi>Cain?</hi> who ſcoft at righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> but his own ſon <hi>Cham?</hi> by whom was that vertuous and religious Lady <hi>Barbara</hi> put to death, for imbracing the Chriſtian faith, but by her own father <hi>Dioſcorus?</hi> who made <hi>Serena</hi> the Empreſſe a <hi>Martyr,</hi> for her faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but her own husband <hi>Diocleſian?</hi> who helped to burn <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> but <hi>Bourne,</hi> whoſe life he had formerly ſaved? And laſtly, By whom was our <hi>Saviour Christ</hi> betrayed, but by his own <hi>Diſciple Judas?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <p>VVHerein conſiſts their unlikeneſſe and contratiety?<note place="margin">Convert.</note> 
                  <hi>Miniſter.</hi> There be more differences between the <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God</hi> and the <hi>children of the devil,</hi> then there are between <hi>men</hi> and <hi>beaſts.</hi> But principally they differ in their <hi>judgements, affections</hi> and <hi>actions.</hi> How they differ in their judgements and affections, I have ſhewn upon another occaſion. How in their actions and practice (which occaſions the greateſt ſtrife and diſcord) I will acquaint you as briefly as I can.</p>
               <p>There is nothing more common then for all ſorts and kindes of men; to <hi>hate, ſcorn, perſecute, reproach, revile, accuſe, ſlander</hi> and <hi>condemn</hi> the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>becauſe their own works are evil</hi> and wicked, and <hi>the others good, holy and righteous.</hi> As wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore ſlew <hi>Cain</hi> his brother, ſaith S. <hi>John,</hi> but becauſe <hi>his own works were evil and his brothers good,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.12? Why was <hi>Joſeph</hi> accuſed of his <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> for an adulterer, and thereupon committed to priſon, but becauſe he would not be an adulterer like her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39? yea it was his party coloured coat, compoſed of all kinds of graces and bleſſings, that formerly procured his bretherens hate. And what is it that <hi>Jobs wife</hi> expoſtulates with him about, but his integrity? as if ſhe took it ill that he took it no worſe, his patience made her impatient. Wherefore was holy <hi>David,</hi> as himſelf complains almoſt in every Pſalm, <hi>had in deriſion, hated, ſlandered, reviled, contemned, and made a proverb and ſong of the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards and other wicked man which ſate in the gate:</hi> but becauſe <hi>he followed the things that were good and pleaſing unto God, and in him put his truſt?</hi> Pſal. 11.2. and 22.6, 7, 8. and 37.14. and 69.10, 11, 12. And laſtly (for I might be endleſſe in the proſecution of this,) Why were all the <hi>juſt</hi> in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, <hi>had in abomination, and mockt of the wicked?</hi> but becauſe <hi>they were upright in their way, and holy in their converſation,</hi> Prov. 29.27. Or thoſe numberleſſe <hi>Martyrs, whoſe ſouls S.</hi> John <hi>ſaw under the Altar,</hi> Revel. 6.9. <hi>killed?</hi> but <hi>for the word of God, and for the teſtimony which they maintained?</hi> And the <hi>Maſter</hi> himſelf? not for any evil as themſelves are forced to confeſſe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.37. Which examples ſufficiently prove, that <hi>that great Dragon the Devil,</hi> and theſe his ſubjects, are <hi>wroth</hi> with none, but <hi>the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151476:11"/>and the remnant of her ſeed, which keep the commandements of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus,</hi> Revel. 12, 17. All was quiet at <hi>Epheſus</hi> before S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> came thither; but then <hi>there aroſe no ſmall ſtrife about that way,</hi> Acts 19.23, &amp;c. A <hi>wolfe</hi> flies not upon a painted <hi>ſheep:</hi> we can with delight look upon the picture of a <hi>Toad:</hi> It is your active Chriſtian that is moſt ſpighted and perſecuted. As how many with us may complain with <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that <hi>becauſe they live a godly life themſelves, and call upon others to do the ſame, they are curſed of every one, and counted contentious,</hi> Jer. 15.10. It faring with many as it did with <hi>Caius Selius,</hi> of whom the <hi>heathen</hi> were wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to ſay, that he was a good man, but he was a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> Yea let but a ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k of fervent devotion break out in a family, all the reſt are up in cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; as when <hi>bells ring diſorderly,</hi> every one is ready with his <hi>bucket</hi> to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ench the fire:</hi> diſgraced he muſt be for a <hi>puritane:</hi> but only by <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eans.</hi> Indifferency ſtrives to daſh zeal out of countenance. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, whereſoever Chriſt comes, there will be oppoſition. <hi>When Chriſt was born, all Ieruſalem was troubled, and Herod cut the throats of all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Bethlem:</hi> ſo when <hi>Chriſt</hi> is born in any man, the ſoul is in an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore, and <hi>Satan</hi> with his inſtruments are ready to kill in him every good motion, though it be never ſo little a babe. You cannot anger a wicked man worſe, then to do well: yea he hates you more bitterly for this, and the credit you gain thereby, then if you had cheated him of his patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with your own diſcredit. Whereas, if a man will but bare them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in their ſins, drink, ſwear, temporize, contemn holineſſe, miſpend his time, haunt Taverns, play the good fellow, and do as the reſt do; he ſhall have the approbation and good word of the greateſt number. Yea if none would be preciſe in their actions, nor reprove others for their evil courſes; if they would but be prophane and wicked, and make no bones of ſinne; their malice would ceaſe, and we ſhould not have a <hi>puritane</hi> or <hi>roundhead</hi> in all the world.</p>
               <p>Neither is <hi>Chriſt a ſigne to be ſpoken againſt of many in Babylon or Aſſiria,</hi> but of many in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Luk. 2.34. where religion is profeſt publikely: Yea when ſincerity is wanting, the neerer the <hi>line</hi> with any oppoſition, the greater <hi>eclipſe.</hi> The <hi>Gadareans</hi> but beſought <hi>Chriſt</hi> to depart; his own country men drave him out and caſt him down headlong, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.29. And who was his greateſt enemy, but his greateſt friend, even one of his houſhold <hi>Chaplins?</hi> and who but <hi>Ieremies familiars watched for his halting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea commonly, vertue fares hardeſt from ſuch as ſhould and ſeem to uphold her; for the chief perſecutors of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his followers, are not profeſt <hi>Atheists,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Iews,</hi> but, ſuch as hold ſome great place in the <hi>Church.</hi> And intruders upon other mens right, can endure any man how bad ſoever rather to live by them, then the ſervants of him whom they intrude upon; as you may ſee, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.33, to 39. where thoſe <hi>farmers</hi> of the <hi>vineyard</hi> did not kill the theeves, robbers and ſpoylers of the vineyard; but the ſervants, yea and the ſon too; and the end of all was, that they might take the inheritance. However, it hath been the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, almoſt of all that have written, that they have ſuffered moſt, from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151476:12"/>ſuch as profeſt the ſame faith and religion with them.</p>
               <p>And ſo much touching the main difference between the ſeed of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and the ſeed of the woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX.</head>
               <p>I Might go on, and ſhew you that as they hate and perſecute the godly becauſe they <hi>do well,</hi> ſo likewiſe becauſe they <hi>fare well,</hi> and are accepted before them. As why <hi>was Cain wroth with his Brother Abel,</hi> and after ſlew him, as affirmeth the holy Ghoſt, but <hi>becauſe the Lord had reſpect unto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel and to his offering, but unto Cain and his offering he had no reſpect,</hi> Gen. 4.4, 5. Why did <hi>Eſau</hi> hate <hi>Jacob,</hi> and purpoſe to kill him, but becauſe of the bleſſing wherewith his father bleſſed him? <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41. <hi>Iſaacks</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing bred <hi>Eſaus</hi> hate. Again, wherefore did the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> and <hi>Abimelech</hi> envy <hi>Iſaac?</hi> ſtop up his wells, and baniſh him from them, but <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord ſo abundantly bleſſed Iſaac?</hi> as appears <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.12, to 18. Wherefore did <hi>Joſephs Brethren</hi> hate him, not being able to ſpeak peaceably unto him, and after ſell him into <hi>Egipt?</hi> but becauſe his father more favoured him, and they feared he ſhould reign over them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.4, to 9. If <hi>Joſeph</hi> be his fathers darling, he is his brethrens eye-ſore. Wherefore did <hi>Saul</hi> perſecute <hi>David,</hi> and purſue after him from place to place to take away his life, but becauſe he was ſo praiſed and preferred of the people before himſelf? and <hi>the Lord was with David, and proſpered him in every thing he took in hand,</hi> 1 Sam. 18.12, 13, 28, 29. <hi>Davids</hi> ſucceſſe is <hi>Sauls</hi> vexation: yea, he findes not ſo much pleaſure in his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as vexation in the proſperity of <hi>David?</hi> And laſtly (for I paſſe by the <hi>Elder Brothers</hi> envy in the <hi>Parable</hi> againſt his <hi>younger Brother,</hi> when his Father ſo royally entertained him at his return, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.28. which is meant of the <hi>Jews</hi> envying the <hi>Gentiles</hi> converſion, and many the like inſtances.) Why was <hi>Eliab</hi> wroth with his younger brother? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28. but becauſe he ſhould be more exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And I doubt whether <hi>Davids</hi> brethren were more <hi>glad</hi> that <hi>Goliah</hi> was ſlain, or <hi>angry</hi> that he was ſlain by their brother: For envy is ſick if her neighbour be well, and the good mans honour is the envious mans torment: as it fared betwen <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Mirdecai;</hi> as hereafter the glory of Chriſt ſhall adde to theſe Reprobates confuſion, when they are driven to confeſſe <hi>this is he whom we once had in deriſion,</hi> Luke 13.28. I might alſo apply all this to many in our times. As why do many mens hearts riſe againſt every holy man they meet? as ſome ſtomacks riſe at the ſight of ſweet-meats: Why do all drunkards and vitious livers hate the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious? and ſo belch out their enmity and ſpleen againſt them, in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſpreading of ſlanders as they do: but although partly to reſcue themſelves from contempt, and to procure a contrary eſteem by putting a foul and ugly vizard upon vertue, and decking up vice in a gorgeous and comely attire; yet chiefly becauſe <hi>they partake of the divine nature, and are one with the Father and the Son,</hi> John 17.14, 21, 22. 2 Cor. 6.18. I might I ſay be large upon this, and many the like, but I muſt only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151476:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <p>INdeed if there were any ſpeaking to ſuch, I would wiſh them to beware of this ſin of all other ſins in the world. For the <hi>godly are unto God as the ſignet upon his right hand,</hi> Jer. 22.24. yea, <hi>as the apple of his own eye,</hi> Zech. 2.8. And whatſoever wrongs and contumelies are done to them, he accounteth as done to himſelf, as they may ſee <hi>Pſa.</hi> 44.22. and 69.7. and 74.4, 10, 18, 22, 23. and 83.2, 5, 6. and 89.50, 51. and 139.20. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. and 9.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.22. and 25.45. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.17. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.4.22, 23.28. and <hi>Act.</hi> 5.39. and 9.4, 5. <hi>Job</hi> 9.4. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.18, 20, 21, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.11. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</p>
               <p>Yea, thirdly, God hath expreſly told them, that <hi>whoſoever ſhall offend one of thoſe little ones that beleeve in him, it were better for him that a millſtone were hung about his neck, and that he were caſt into the Sea,</hi> Mat. 18.6. And that <hi>he will deſtroy them for ever, and root them out of the Land of the living, whoſe tongues imagine miſchief, and are like a ſharp razor that cutteth deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, loving to speak evil more then good,</hi> Pſa. 52.2. to 8. That <hi>he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſuch as perſecute his children, and deſtroy them with a double deſtruction,</hi> Jer. 17.18. yea, That <hi>he will render unto their enemies ſevenfold into their boſome, their reproach wherewith they have reproached the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 79.12. In <hi>fine,</hi> That <hi>he will reign upon them ſnares of fire and brimſtome, with ſtorms and tempeſts,</hi> Pſa. 11.6. And after all <hi>caſt them into a Furnace of fire, where ſhall be wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth for evermore:</hi> When the <hi>juſt</hi> whom they now deſpiſe <hi>ſhall ſhine as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> Many are apt to think, that becauſe they uſe their tongues only they are no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors: but they ſhall hereafter hear themſelves ſtiled ſo in their <hi>Bill of Inditement, Iſhmael</hi> did but flowt <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>he perſecuted him,</hi> Gal. 4.29. God cals the ſcorning of his ſervants by no better a name then perſecution; and will thereafter reward it, perhaps in this life, as it fared with thoſe <hi>two and fourty little children,</hi> 2 Kin. 2.24. who <hi>were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured of wilde bears,</hi> only <hi>for nicknaming Eliſha:</hi> Or as it did with <hi>Felix</hi> who for one malicious ſcoff did nothing day and night but vomit bloud, till his unhappy ſoul was fetcht from his wretched carcaſſe. And <hi>Phere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydes</hi> who was conſumed by worms alive for giving Religion but a nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, a ſmall matter if thou maiſt be made judge. Or as it did with <hi>Lucian,</hi> who for barking againſt Religion like a dog, was by the juſt judgement of God devoured of dogs. Or as it did with <hi>Nightingale</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Crondall</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> who was ſtruck dead in the Pulpit while he was belching out his ſpleen againſt Religion and zealous profeſſors of the Goſpel. Or as it did with <hi>Steven Gerdiner</hi> who would not ſit down to dinner till the news came of the good Biſhops burnt at <hi>Oxford,</hi> but then came out rejoycing, and ſaying to the <hi>Duke of Norfolk,</hi> now let us go to dinner; but it was the laſt that ever he eat for it. Or as it fared with <hi>Arundell</hi> Archbiſhop of Canterbury, and <hi>Steven Gardiner</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> who putting to ſilence both the <hi>Word of God</hi> and thoſe that purely preach it, were themſelves put to ſilence, and ſo ſmitten in their tongues, that they could not ſwallow their meat, nor ſpeak for a good
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151476:13"/>ſpace before they died. The time would be too ſhort to tell of <hi>Cham</hi> whoſe ſcoffing only brought his Fathers curſe, and Gods upon that. Of the Spies that brought a ſcandall upon the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> (as theſe do upon the way of truth) and made all the people to murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes:</hi> who <hi>died by a plague from the Lord,</hi> and were not permitted to enter into it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.37. And the like, which God hath inflicted upon men even in this life: though I count it a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcy to ſmart here (if they die penitent) rather then be reſerved to thoſe flames which are eaſeleſſe and endleſſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it is frivolous to ſay they only uſe their tongues. It is not ſo materiall what thou doſt as what thou deſireſt; the very purpoſe of treaſon (though the fact be hindred) is treaſon, not the <hi>outward action</hi> but the <hi>inward affection</hi> is all in all with God, who meaſures the work by the will, as men meaſure the will by the work.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <p>NOw the reaſon why Chriſt takes what is done to his members as if it were done to himſelf; and why he will ſo ſeverely puniſh; 'tis, for that their ſpight and malice is principally againſt God and Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: <hi>For thy ſake</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>David</hi>) <hi>are we killed all the day long, and counted as ſheep for the ſlaughter,</hi> Pſalm 44.22. True, they are ſo blinde that they think they love God, or at leaſt do not hate him: but Chriſt himſelf ſaith expreſly, <hi>They have hated both me and my Father,</hi> John 15.23, 24. where he repeats the words twice. Nor will they ſpare when ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſhall ſeize upon them; openly, and expreſly to blaſpheme the God of Heaven to his face, as the holy Ghoſt twice affirmeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9, 11. Common eyes may be cheated with eaſie pretences, but he that looks through the heart at the face, knows that the foundation of all their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and enmity to us, is their hatred againſt God and Chriſt the chief of the <hi>Womans ſeed,</hi> even as when Satan ſlew <hi>Iobs</hi> ſervants, his malice was againſt <hi>Job:</hi> Or as when <hi>Saul</hi> darted a ſpear at <hi>Jonathan,</hi> his ſpight was againſt <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 20.33. He that loves not the members was never a friend to the head, He that wrongs the wife is no friend to the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: he loves neither that vilifies either; yea, they that hate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile the godly becauſe they are godly, as theſe do; (for they could love our perſons well enough if we were not conſcionable:) hate and revile God himſelf; and they that fight againſt the grace of the ſpirit, fight againſt the ſpirit, whoſe grace it is: and whatſoever wrong is done to one of Chriſts little ones, is done unto him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.45. <hi>Saul, Saul,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, ſeeing him make havock of the Church, <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me:</hi> Acts 9.4, 5. It is an idle miſpriſion to ſever the ſence of an injury done to any of the members from the head, ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. It contents the dog to gnaw the ſtone, when he cannot reach the thrower. It was well-pleaſing to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſince he could not catch <hi>David,</hi> that he might have the bloud of <hi>Ahimelech,</hi> who uſed him ſo friendly, and releeved him in his great diſtreſſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. So though theſe men cannot wreak their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151476:13"/>upon God, he being out of their power and reach: yet that they may do him all the miſchief they can, have at his <hi>Image;</hi> they will wreak it upon his children in whom his ſpirit dwells. As the <hi>Panther</hi> will fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſault the <hi>picture,</hi> for the inveterate and deadly hatred which he bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to man. It being as true of malice as it is of love; that it will creep where it cannot go. And ſo much for the clearing of your judgement: I come now to the uſe and application of the whole. And,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, It may ſerve to inform every man whether he be of the <hi>Serpents ſeed, a childe of the devil,</hi> as he came into the world: Or regenerate, and ſo become of the <hi>womans ſeed,</hi> a childe of God, and member of Chriſt. For as our Saviour ſaith, ſpeaking of <hi>falſe Prophets, By their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> ſo I of the ſeed of the Serpent, and children of the devil; by theſe two and twenty fruits or properties of enmity before ſpoken of, you ſhall know them, as well as you ſhall know the life by breathing, or the day by its light. Wherefore all ye that reade reflect and caſt your eyes on theſe examples, which are ſuch lively emblemes and repreſentations of your ſelves: if you be the <hi>Serpents ſeed,</hi> and yet in your ſins. Yea, let it make you tremble; For know aſſuredly, that if this ſpawn of enmity remain in you, if any of theſe waies, you perſecute Chriſt in his members, or but hate the good, becauſe they will not be ſo evill as you are, you have not caſt off this Serpentine quality, which you drew from the loins of old <hi>Adam:</hi> but it is an infallible ſign that you are of the Serpents ſeed, and children of the devil; enemies to, and haters of God and all goodneſſe, the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Cain,</hi> or <hi>Cain</hi> himſelf in another perſon, and without anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble repentance, your portion ſhall be with <hi>Cain,</hi> and the reſt of that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed crew. I have ſhewn you what God in his word ſpeaks, and proved that your condition is no whit better then the condition of <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and <hi>Haman,</hi> and <hi>Doeg,</hi> and <hi>Shemy,</hi> and <hi>Rahſheke,</hi> and their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; yea, no glaſſe can more lively repreſent your faces, then this Book doth your hearts. Only this is the miſery, as when a childe beholds his own face in a glaſſe; he thinks he ſees another childes face, and not his own, ſo fares it with you. What do you look that Chriſt Jeſus himſelf from heaven ſhould call to you ſeverally by name as he did to <hi>Saul;</hi> and ſay, Ho <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſuch an one, or Ho <hi>Elimas</hi> ſuch an one: <hi>Why doſt thou perſecute me? I am Jeſus whom thon perſecuteſt,</hi> Acts 9.4, 5. Which yet if he ſhould, it were no more in effect then he hath often done: nor would you be any more warned or reclaimed by it, as is evident by the example of <hi>Hazael,</hi> 2 King. 8.12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by what <hi>Abraham</hi> told <hi>Dives,</hi> Luk. 16.31. For God in his word tels every one of you plainly, that Satan is the God of all unbeleevers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. And their King <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.30. and 12.31. And their father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>John</hi> 8.44. And that <hi>they are all his ſervants, kept by the devil in a ſnare, and taken captive of him at his will,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.26. And that <hi>he ruleth by and worketh his pleaſure in all the children
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151476:14"/>of diſobedience,</hi> Eph. 2.2, 3. And makes it manifeſt to all (whom the devil hath not blinded) that you of all men in the world, are thoſe unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and children of diſobedience in whom he rules. And yet poor ſouls you know it not. As thoſe four hundred of <hi>Ahabs Prophets,</hi> in whom this evil ſpirit ſpake, did not know that Satan ſpake by them, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22. Neither did <hi>Judas</hi> know when he eat the ſop, that <hi>Satan entred into him,</hi> and put it into his heart to betray Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.2. Neither do <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> (when they caſt the ſervants of God into priſon) once imagine, that the devil makes them his <hi>jaylors,</hi> but he doth ſo; whence that phraſe of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>The devil ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon,</hi> Revel. 2.10. They are his inſtruments, but he is the principall Authour. Neither did <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> once think, that Satan had filled their hearts, or put that lye into their mouths which they were ſtrook dead for, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. yet the holy Ghoſt tels us plainly that he did ſo, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. No, <hi>Eve</hi> in Paradiſe had not the leaſt ſuſpition that it was Satan that ſpake to her by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; nor <hi>Adam</hi> that it was the devils minde in her mouth, his heart in her lips, when tempted to eat the forbidden fruit. Nor did <hi>David</hi> once dream, that it was Satan which <hi>moved him to number the people,</hi> 1 Chron. 21.1. Much leſſe did <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſo dearly loved Chriſt, imagine that he was ſet on by Satan to tempt his own Lord and Maſter with thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate words, <hi>Maſter, pity thy ſelf,</hi> for if Chriſt had pitied himſelf, <hi>Peter</hi> and all the world had periſhed: yet he was ſo, which occaſioned Chriſt to anſwer him, <hi>Get thee behinde me Satan,</hi> Mat. 16.22, 23. But conſider, For hence we may argue, that if Satan can make the beſt and wiſeſt of Gods children and ſervants (who <hi>have the very appearance of evil,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.22. Jude 23. Epheſ. 5.27. 2 Pet. 3.14. Jam. 1.27. have the eye of faith, and the ſpirits direction, and know the minde of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12, 13, 15, 16. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.14.) do him ſuch ſervice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wittingly, and beſides their intention: how much more can he prevail with, and make uſe of his own ſervants and children, that delight only in wickedneſſe, and have not the leaſt knowledge of, or ability to diſcern ſpirituall things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. yea, if Satan can perſwade you (as he hath done millions) that you do God good ſervice in perſecuting his children as the <hi>Jews</hi> formerly did, <hi>in putting his Prophets to death;</hi> as Chriſt himſelf expreſly tels us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.2. What can he not perſwade them to? what work or ſervice can he not put them upon? without letting them know, that he their God, Father, and Maſter, ſpeaks in and acts by them. Whence that of <hi>Solomon, There is a way that ſeemeth, right unto a man, but the iſſues thereof are the waies of death,</hi> Proverbs 14.12. Whence ſo many have been ſo ſtrangely, and ſo wofully deluded: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a few inſtances very remarkable. There was a Monk poyſoned <hi>Henry the ſeventh Emperour of Germany</hi> with the ſacramentall bread, and thought he did God good ſervice in ſo doing. So did the <hi>Powder-Traitors,</hi> when they intended to blow up the whole State. <hi>Maximinian</hi> thought the bloud of Chriſtians would be an acceptable ſacrifice to his gods. So <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Spain,</hi> thought of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151476:14"/>
                  <hi>Lutherans</hi> bloud in their Dominions. In the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>Council of Toledo</hi> it was enacted, that the <hi>King of Spain</hi> ſhould ſuffer none to live in his dominions that profeſſed not the <hi>Roman Catholike</hi> Religion: Whereupon King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> having hardly eſcaped ſhipwrack, as he returned from the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> ſaid, he was delivered by the ſingular providence of God to root out <hi>Lutheraniſm,</hi> which he preſently began to do: profeſſing that he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have no ſubjects then ſuch; In which opinion many depart, but as men go to a Lottery, with heads full of hopes, but return with hearts full of blanks: ſo will it one day fare with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV.</head>
               <p>NOr are they few in number, that (with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> before his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) do perſecute the people of <hi>God,</hi> even <hi>out of zeal to the traditions of their fathers,</hi> Gal. 1.13, 14. Phil. 3.6. <hi>Many walk,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul, that are enemies to the croſse of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.18. If many in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> time, many more now. Yea S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>number of thoſe whom Satan ſhall thus deceive, is as the ſand of the ſea,</hi> Rev. 20.8. and 13.16. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.22. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.13, 14. and 20.16. and 22.14.</p>
               <p>And experience it ſelf tells us, that it is the caſe almoſt of who not: For this ſin is ſo epidemicall, that take forty men where you pleaſe, <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Country,</hi> as they dwell, paſſe the ſtreets, or ſit in the <hi>Church,</hi> and nine and thirty of them are malignants to the power of Religion. As for other ſins, one man is given to <hi>luſt,</hi> another to <hi>intemperance,</hi> a third to <hi>ſwearing,</hi> a fourth to <hi>couſening;</hi> ſome to more then one, ſome to all of them; but who is not tainted with this ſin? who is not an open or ſccret enemy to holineſſe, by reaſon of that generall contempt which is caſt upon profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors? Yea who is there, even of thoſe that have reſigned up their pride, and their luſt, and their lying, and their couſening, and what other ſins they have been prone to, with whom this ſin doth not remain? as being carried away with miſpriſions, ſurmiſes, and weak opinions raiſed from meer prejudice and ſhadowes of things: And which is worſt of all, it hath by long cuſtom, taken ſuch deep root in mens hearts, that I look never to ſee it mended till Chriſt comes in the clouds. Only it behoves all men, even every living ſoul of us, to ſee that himſelf be none of that numberleſſe number, whom Satan thus cunningly prevails withall, And not without need, though moſt are apt to flatter themſelves: for this is an infallible rule, every man is either of the <hi>ſeed of the Serpent,</hi> or of the <hi>ſeed of the woman,</hi> Gen. 3.15. the <hi>childe of God,</hi> or the <hi>childe of the Devil,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.10. either <hi>haters of Religion,</hi> or <hi>hated for Religion,</hi> Matth. 10.22. and 24.9. either one of <hi>this world,</hi> or one that <hi>Chriſt hath choſen out of the world,</hi> Joh. 15.19.</p>
               <p>Though all the divels children are not alike malicious, neither do they ſo openly manifeſt that enmity which is in their hearts: for ſome tranſcend this way, as <hi>Doog</hi> did the reſt of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants another way; you ſhall know ſuch an one, yea all men ſhall know ſuch to be the <hi>divels children</hi> by theſe few marks. He will hate a man to the death, though he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151476:15"/>have nothing to condemn him but his being holy. His hatred is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate and univerſall, that he ſpends all his wit, in frothy ſcoffs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives againſt the whole people of God: And nothing ſo tickles his ſpleen or glads his heart, as that diſcourſe which may moſt ſhame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, diſgrace Religion, and diſhonour God: with <hi>Feſtus</hi> he calls <hi>zeal madneſse,</hi> and <hi>Religion fooliſhneſſe</hi> with <hi>Michall.</hi> He will ſharpen his tongue in gall, and dip his pen in poiſon, to dſgrace the graces of God in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. He hates zeal and devotion ſo inveterately, that he can in no wiſe bare with it in others. He is ſo deſperately wicked, that he cannot indure ſo much as the ſight of godlineſſe: like him in <hi>Seneca,</hi> who was ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully idle, that his ſides would ake to ſee another work. He is juſt like the <hi>Jews</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Acts</hi> 13. who when they <hi>ſaw a great company at Pauls Sermon, were filled with envy, and fell to contradiction and blaſphemy,</hi> ver. 45. Or the <hi>High Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who when our <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aviour</hi> was ſo flockt after, ſaid among themſelves, <hi>perceive ye not, behold the world goeth after him; and if we let him thus alone, all men will beleeve in him,</hi> Joh. 11.48. and 12.19. being like the <hi>dog</hi> in the <hi>manger,</hi> that will neither <hi>eat bay</hi> himſelf, nor ſuffer the <hi>Horſe.</hi> He is of a reprobate judgement touching actions and perſons, eſteeming good evil and evil good. And is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately wicked, that he will mock his admoniſhers, ſcoff at the means to be ſaved, and make himſelf merry with his own damnation. As good men by their godly admonition and vertuous example, draw all they can to <hi>heaven;</hi> ſo he by his ſubtill allurements and wicked example, draws all he can to <hi>hell.</hi> He regards more the blaſts of mens breath, then the fire of Gods wroth. He will boldly do what God forbids, and yet confidently hope to eſcape what he threatens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now if you know any that do thus, you may be ſure he is of <hi>that wicked one,</hi> Joh. 8.44. Matth. 23.33. 1 Joh. 3.10. For none but a <hi>Cane</hi> or a <hi>devil</hi> in condition, will envy <hi>becauſe his own works are evil and his brothers good.</hi> Neither could he do ſo if the <hi>devil</hi> were not in his heart. Neither can there be a greater argument of a foul ſoul, then the deriding of holy ſervices. Yea to ſcoff at Religion is the very depth of ſinne; ſuch an one is upon the very threſhold of <hi>hell,</hi> as being ſet down in a reſolute contempt of all goodneſſe. And ſo much of the firſt Uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXV.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, We may learn from the <hi>originall of this enmity,</hi> that to be without reproaches and perſecutions, we may rather wiſh then hope. For what peace can we look for, between the ſeed of the ſerpent and the ſeed of the woman, ſeeing God himſelf from the beginning hath ſet them at enmity: yea once to expect it, were an effect of frenzy not of hope.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, From <hi>the continuance of it in all ages;</hi> and in that all the godly that have gone before us have been envied, hated, traduced, nick-named and perſecuted by wicked men, and all that come after us ſhall be: let no particular <hi>member of the Church,</hi> look to fare better then the <hi>whole body.</hi> We ſee the <hi>Patriarks</hi> went this way, the <hi>Prophets</hi> this way, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151476:15"/>this way, the <hi>Martyrs</hi> this way; this way went all the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>ſervants of God,</hi> and do we look for an eaſier way. Yea if the deareſt of Gods children in former ages, have ſuffered ſo much for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> been put to ſuch cruell deaths and torments for keeping of a good conſcience: let us praiſe the <hi>Lord</hi> who hath dealt with us far otherwiſe: and pray for <hi>good Magistrates,</hi> to whom next under <hi>God</hi> we owe the thanks. Yea if our fore-fathers ſo willingly underwent thoſe <hi>fiery trials,</hi> let none for ſhame ſhrink under the burthen of an <hi>airy triall</hi> only. For he will never endure a <hi>blow,</hi> that cannot concoct a foul <hi>word:</hi> He that is diſcouraged, and made to return with an <hi>Iſhmaelitiſh perſecution of the tongue,</hi> how would he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſitian,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Marian times?</hi> He that is ſo frighted with a <hi>ſquib,</hi> how would he endure the mouth of a <hi>Cannon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, If our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf ſuffered ſo much and ſo many wayes as he did, being <hi>the only begotten Son of God, full of grace and truth:</hi> Let none of us hope to be free from ſuffering, or think it a ſtrange thing when he doth ſuffer for well doing. For <hi>the diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord: If they have perſecuted Chriſt, they will perſecute you alſo,</hi> Joh. 15.20. <hi>If they have called the Maſter of the houſe Belzebub, how much more them of his houſhold,</hi> Matth. 10.25. Yea ſenceleſſe were it once to think, that the ſame enmity which ſpared not to ſtrike at the <hi>head,</hi> will forbare the weakeſt and remoteſt <hi>limbe.</hi> It was the lot of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and muſt be of all his followers, to do good and ſuffer evil. Nor can we elſe be conformable to <hi>Chriſt our head,</hi> or be like our <hi>elder brother; who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated through afflictions:</hi> and <hi>we muſt ſuffer with him, that we may be alſo glorified with him,</hi> Rom. 8.17. Yea, <hi>hereunto we are called,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter; For Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21. <hi>Suffering</hi> is the way to <hi>reigning: through many tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt we enter into the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Acts 14.22. Even as <hi>Chriſt</hi> had his <hi>paſſion</hi> before his <hi>aſſention,</hi> and bare his <hi>croſſe</hi> before he ware his <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And what greater promotion can fleſh and bloud be capable of, then a conformity to the <hi>Lord of glory?</hi> Who would not be ambitious of the ſame entertainment which <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf had? <hi>Chriſt</hi> wore a <hi>Crown of thorns</hi> for me, and ſhall I grutch to ware this paper cap for him, ſaid <hi>John Hus</hi> when they put one upon him, that had ugly devils painted on it, with the Title of <hi>Hereſie.</hi> And what ſaid a <hi>French Martyr,</hi> when a rope was put about his fellow, Give me that <hi>gold chain,</hi> and <hi>dub</hi> me a <hi>Knight</hi> of that <hi>Noble Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore arm thou us O God, with an expectation of that evil which we cannot avoid: yea make thou us as ſtrong as Satan and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are malicious, and then let them do their worſt.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>If the brother perſecute the brother, the ſon the father, the parent the childe, the husband his wife, the diſciple his Lord:</hi> think it not ſtrange to be perſecuted of any; for they which are not perſecuted are perſecutors themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151476:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVI.</head>
               <p>SIxtly, Since we can expect no peace from the Serpents ſeed; let as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as are of the womans ſeed and of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſide, unanimouſly hold to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and joyn againſt their common enemy. <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> are much to be commended, who when they perceived the <hi>Arians</hi> to improve a difference between them, to the prejudice of the <hi>Orthodox;</hi> ſoon recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled themſelves, and <hi>united their forces</hi> together againſt the <hi>common enemy.</hi> O that all <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>orthodox Chriſtians,</hi> whether <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> would joyn together againſt <hi>Atheists</hi> and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and not ſo croſſe, contradict and aſperſe each other, if they never ſo little differ in judgement about circumſtantials. As let but two <hi>maſtiffs</hi> be jarring be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves; when the Bear comes, they forget private ſtrife to aſſoil their common Enemy. And certainly they might be as firm friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to truth, although they were not ſuch bitter enemies to peace. For a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the caſe ſtandeth, it is hard to determine whether they more intend to do God ſervice; or really do the devil and his inſtruments ſervice.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, If the Lord have put this enmity between us and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: here is warrant in oppoſing, comfort in ſuffering. If the ſeed of the woman fight on Chriſts ſide, and they have Gods word for their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, they are ſure to have him aſſiſt them, and prevent their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And is not that God we fight for able enough to vindicate all our wrongs?</p>
               <p>Eighthly, If a Chriſtian in reſpect of his hard ſtraits between Gods Law on the one ſide, and the malignant world on the other; may fitly be compared to the <hi>Gibbionites:</hi> who, if they made not their peace with <hi>Joſhu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> muſt die by ſtrangers; and if they did make their peace with him; they muſt die by neighbours. Or to <hi>Suſanna</hi> who if ſhe did yeeld unto the <hi>two Elders</hi> muſt loſe her chaſtity, and hazard her ſoul; and if ſhe did not yeeld, ſhe muſt looſe her life. For we have a Wolf by the ears which we can neither ſtay nor let go with ſafety. If we ſeek to pleaſe God by a holy life we diſpleaſe the world, and that will hate and vex us: If we ſeek to pleaſe the world we diſpleaſe God, and he will hate and condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us: for their commands are diametrically contrary, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.18, 19. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of two evils let us chooſe the leaſt; let us not tun into the fire to avoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſmoak. It is better to have the mocks and flouts of men on earth then the grinning mocks and laſhes of the devils in hell. Let us not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like thoſe white-livered Rulers, <hi>John</hi> 12. <hi>that loved the praiſe of men mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then the praiſe of God.</hi> Nor like <hi>Peter,</hi> who denied his Lord, and curſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf, to get credit amongſt a curſed crew: For what are their word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other then as a <hi>boys-ſquib,</hi> that only flaſhes, and cracks, and ſtinks, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is nothing. And thoſe that hang their faith on ſuch mens lips, do b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> like <hi>Ixion</hi> embrace a cloud inſtead of <hi>Juno.</hi> Yea, well may he claim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Boat-ſwayns place in <hi>Barkleys Ship of ſools,</hi> that will ſell his ſoul for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> few good words from wicked mens tongues.</p>
               <p>But what will ſome object: For many with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> do owe Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſome good will, but they dare not be known of it: like <hi>Nicodemus</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151476:16"/>would ſteal to heaven, ſo no body might ſee them; they would pleaſe God, yet ſo as they might not diſpleaſe others nor themſelves. Like the young man in the Goſpel; they would follow Chriſt, ſo Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded no other conditions to them then what they like of. And theſe will be ready to ſay, what need we publiſh our ſelves or our faith: can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not men ſerve God in ſecret, whereby they may avoid the worlds taunts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Profeſſion can no more be ſeparated from the truth of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion then light from the Sun, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10, 11. True fire (not painted) cannot but heat, break forth, and aſcend, That which is not gold, may gliſter, but that which is gold cannot chooſe but gliſter. The fruit will ſhew what the Tree is: It is but <hi>a dead faith which hath no works,</hi> Jam. 2.17.20, 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.30, 31.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Unleſſe a man keep his lips alwaies ſeal'd up; he muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſemble, or elſe his language will bewray what countreyman he is. Neither can he avoid telling it, for admit a man be in adverſe company, they will ſo beſet him with queſtions, and draw him on, and pick it out of him, that without an abſurd ſilence he muſt ſhew an inclination one way. Or if he do not, they will gather as much by his ſilence as by his ſpeech. Or</p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, A man cannot diſſent from their wicked cuſtoms, he cannot refuſe <hi>to run with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot,</hi> in drinking, ſwearing, prophaning the Lords day, and the like; much leſſe can he admoniſh them, and ſo diſcharge his conſcience; but he makes too great a ſhew, and his profeſſion troubles them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, As this cannot be, ſo it ought not to be; and that for many ſolid reaſons and grounds taken out of <hi>Gods word,</hi> as I have largely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in my <hi>Cure of Miſpriſion,</hi> and as you may ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7, 8, 9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.16. and 10.32, 33. <hi>Mark.</hi> 15.43. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.42, 43. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9, 12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.33. and 12.8. and 8.38, 39. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. and 71.17, 18. and 51.14. and 119.171. and 22.22. and 35.18. and 119.46. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.33. and 10.9, 10. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.20.</p>
               <p>Which being ſo; namely, that there is no pleaſing God nor being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, without being holy and religious; nor no being religious, but it will appear to the world, and ſo occaſion its enmity and perſecution. Let us in no wiſe forbear good actions nor admonitions, be the malignant <hi>world</hi> pleaſed or diſpleaſed with it: yea, let us <hi>ſhine as lights in the midſt of a naughty and crooked generation,</hi> by a blameleſſe and pure life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: thereby <hi>to win others among whom we live,</hi> Phil. 2.15. <hi>Let our light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good works, and glorifie our Father which is in heaven,</hi> Matth. 5.16. Let us <hi>ſhew forth the praiſes of him, who hath called us out of darkneſſe into his marvellous light,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.9. And ſo much the rather, for that our Saviour ſaith expreſly, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me and of my words among this adulterous and ſinfull generation; of him ſhall the ſon of man be aſhamed, when he cometh in the glory of his Father with his holy Angels,</hi> Mark 8.38. Matth. 10.33. Not only not to deny, but not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151476:17"/>to confeſſe the truth is dangerous; as holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 39.1, 2. and the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> found by experience, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10. Not to declare our faith is to deny it, ſaith <hi>Fulgentius.</hi> The <hi>Merozians</hi> oppoſed not, they denied not, they only ſtood ſtill, did nothing, ſaid nothing, yet were they curſed, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.23. He who had not his <hi>dore poſts ſprinckled</hi> with the <hi>bloud of the Paſchall Lambe,</hi> was ſure to ſuffer by the <hi>deſtroying Angel,</hi> Exod. 12.13. And the <hi>fearfull</hi> ſhall go firſt and before other ſinners, <hi>into the lake that burneth with fire and brimstone, which is the ſecond death,</hi> Rev. 21.8. They had bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt <hi>backward</hi> to all good, and therefore ſhall be the <hi>formoſt,</hi> and have the precedency in ſuffering all evill. Wherefore if we love either <hi>Chriſt</hi> or our own <hi>ſouls,</hi> let us never be aſhamed of our <hi>Maſters ſervice,</hi> what ever we ſuffer by waring of his <hi>livery. Be not,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, aſhamed of the teſtimony of our Lord, neither of me his priſoner; but be partakers of the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Goſpel, according to the power of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.8.</p>
               <p>No matter what <hi>Judas</hi> ſaith touching <hi>Maries anoynting our Saviours feet,</hi> ſo long as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf approves of it. Our Saviour did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to heal, and do good <hi>on the Sabbath day:</hi> though the Scribes and Phariſees took it ill; but rather did it the more, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.1, to 12. and 13.31, 32. when <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were charged to ſpeak no more in the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> their anſwer was, we cannot but ſpeak that which we have heard and ſeen, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.20. Let the ſame reſolution be ours ſince the caſe is the ſame.</p>
               <p>Yea let us (with holy <hi>David</hi>) go a ſtrain higher: and when any <hi>Micholl</hi> ſhall ſcoff at us for our zeal, and call us fools; let us be more vile in being more zealous, and we ſhall be had in more honour by <hi>Chriſts</hi> friends: yea our malicious and ſcoffing adverſaries ſhall <hi>honour us by deriding us.</hi> For when vicious men think to tax and traduce us, they do in truth commend us: <hi>their diſpraiſe is a mans honour, their praiſe his diſhonour.</hi> Yea <hi>Terence</hi> a meer <hi>heathen</hi> could ſay, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at to be evil ſpoken of by wicked men, was a glorious and laudable thing. And another, that it is no ſmall credit with the vile, to have a vile eſtimation: which being ſo, let us with <hi>Job take their reproach upon our ſhoulder, and binde it as a Crown unto us,</hi> Job 31.35, 36. At leaſt let us imitate S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who feared the praiſe of good men, and deteſted that of the evil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII.</head>
               <p>NInthly, For a word of advice to the godly: If all naturall men are ſo apt to cenſure the religious, cauſe or no cauſe; And that they have ſo many reaſons to induce them to it: Let us for our Makers, and for our bleſſed Redeemers ſake take heed what we do: leſt we ſhame our profeſſion, and make the way of truth evil ſpoken of, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. Not that I expect their mouths ſhould be ſtopt; for faults they would finde in Chriſt himſelf, did he live amongſt them: neither can God pleaſe them, as you may ſee by their continuall murmuring at the ſeverall paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his providence. Being like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> who were never content, for when they had water they murmure for bread; when they had bread
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151476:17"/>they complain for fleſh: as if they had boarded with God, and he were to provide them dyet: and they good men honeſtly paid for what they took. Onely let them have no juſt occaſion to cenſure and ſpeak evill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> us: for though all true Chriſtians paſſe under their ſharp cenſures, and bitter reproaches: yet I cannot yeeld him a true ſervant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if we belong to <hi>Gods</hi> Family, let us ſhew what houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e come off: not onely by our <hi>Livery,</hi> but by our <hi>living.</hi> The ſons of <hi>God</hi> muſt be <hi>pure, blameleſſe, and without rebuke,</hi> Phil. 2.15. And in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, a Chriſtian was known from another man, onely by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and uprightneſſe of his life and converſation: as <hi>Tertullian</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.</p>
               <p>And great reaſon there is for it: for firſt malice is very quick ſighted, to ſpye faults. Secondly, the Saints (like a <hi>Beacon</hi> upon an hill) have all eyes upon them. Thirdly, vertue or vice in them ſhall be ſure to be margined with a pointing finger. Fourthly, in pureſt things, the ſmalleſt ſpot is ſooner ſeen: then greater ſtaines in baſer ſtuffe: every little <hi>mote</hi> is ſeen, in a <hi>cleer glaſſe,</hi> which will not be diſcerned in an <hi>earthen pitcher.</hi> A ſmall <hi>spot,</hi> or <hi>wart,</hi> or <hi>freckle</hi> in the <hi>face;</hi> is a greater blemiſh, ſooner ſeen, and more noted, then an ugly <hi>skat,</hi> or <hi>botch</hi> in any other part of the <hi>body.</hi> Fifthly, the ſmalleſt ſpot in a religious mans face; ſhall excuſe all the ſores and ulcers in their bodies. Sixthly, in caſe they ſee our lives contrary to our <hi>profeſſion:</hi> they will even proteſt againſt our <hi>Religion;</hi> ſaying, if we did <hi>speak as we think,</hi> we would do <hi>as we ſpeak:</hi> if our Religion were true and good, ſuch as profeſſe it, would live there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Seventhly, in caſe thy <hi>practice</hi> is not ſuitable to thy profeſſion; woe unto thee; for outward profeſſion, where there is want of inward truth, and real practice, doth but help to draw on and aggravate judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Scribes and Phariſees had not heard of ſo many woes, but for their glorious pretences. Yea, had the <hi>Fig-tree</hi> in the <hi>Gospel,</hi> been utterly bare, and leave-leſſe: it had in all probability, eſcaped the curſe.</p>
               <p>Hear this ye vain Hypocrites, that care onely to be thought good: your fair out-ſide, ſhall be ſure to help you to a curſe. And it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for you with Philoſophers, to have honeſty without Religion, then with wicked Chriſtians, to have Religion without honeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
               <p>HEre I might proceed to a uſe of Exhortation. And becauſe it is hard to ſay; whether ignorance or malice does more abound, in theſe ſcoffers, and ſcorners: whether it be more out of the <hi>ſtrength of will,</hi> or <hi>weakneſſe of judgment;</hi> that they thus ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and perſecute us. That theſe <hi>Brute Beaſts</hi> (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> calls them,) <hi>led with ſenſuality; ſpeak evill of the things which they underſtand not,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were requiſite, to exhort, and admoniſh them to uſe all poſſible
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151476:18"/>means; that <hi>God</hi> hath appointed for their renovation. Whereby of the <hi>Serpents ſeed,</hi> and <hi>children of the devil,</hi> they may become the <hi>Children of God,</hi> and <hi>members of Chriſt.</hi> For untill they be born again, they will be like <hi>Nichodemus,</hi> who knew not what it was to be born again, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4. untill they be zealous themſelves, they will be like <hi>Feſtus,</hi> who thought zeal madneſſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.24. untill they be humble themſelves, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey will be like <hi>Michal,</hi> who mocked <hi>David</hi> for his humility, and thought him <hi>a fool for dancing before the Ark,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.16, 20. Yea to all that ſhall periſh, or are for the preſent in a periſhing condition: Religion ſeems no other then fooliſhneſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.</p>
               <p>I might likewiſe go on to a more particular direction, That is, if in caſe any that hear me, have been thus raſhly cenſorious, in making ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of all that the religious do: and find that theſe, or ſome of them, have been the genuine reaſons of their ſo doing, Let them with <hi>Ephraim,</hi> Jer. 31.19. <hi>ſtrike themſelves upon the thigh.</hi> Or with that <hi>Publican,</hi> Luk. 18.13. <hi>ſmite their breaſt:</hi> And with amazement, and indignation ſay: What have I done? I have deeply cenſured and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the generation of the juſt, I have often raiſed an ill report of them, as thoſe <hi>falſe hearted ſpies,</hi> did of the <hi>Land of Canaan.</hi> Numb. 13.32, 33. And that ſcandal paſſing through many mouthes, hath multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed like a ſnow ball: which at beſt hath left ſuch a ſcar of ſuſpition upon their names and credits, that even death it ſelf will not be able to cure. Whereas the Scripture ſayes, <hi>Curſed be he that ſmiteth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſecretly,</hi> Deut. 27.24. And <hi>him that privily ſlandereth his Neighbour, will I deſtroy,</hi> Pſal. 101.5.</p>
               <p>And as I have thus depraved ſome; having more <hi>malice</hi> then <hi>matter</hi> againſt them; ſo I have corrupted others, and foreſtalled their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with prejudice: which may prove the bane of many a ſoul. Woe is me, what ſhall I do; leaſt <hi>God tear me in pieces, and there be none to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver?</hi> I have been long enough inſtrumental to <hi>Satan,</hi> I will now, and hereafter by Gods grace, ſerve <hi>my Saviour:</hi> who is a maſter without compare: O that my <hi>God</hi> would give me a heart, and anſwerable abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be as <hi>faithfull a friend</hi> to Religion, as I have been a <hi>bitter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let this I ſay be thy confeſſion, this thy reſolution: otherwiſe know for a ſurety; that while thou ſcoffeſt at his children, <hi>God</hi> laughes at thee, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.26. And that it will be bitterneſſe in the end: For what evil is done to them, <hi>Chriſt</hi> takes as done to hims <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4. And who ſo thinks holineſſe a crime, or religion a diſgrace, is ſo far from being of his ſpirit, that <hi>was a man after Gods own heart;</hi> that there cannot be a greater argument of a foul ſoul, held by <hi>Satan</hi> in a ſnare, and taken captive of him at his will.</p>
               <p>Neither let <hi>Satan,</hi> nor thy ſeduced and deceitful heart deceive thee; in thinking thou haſt any ſhare in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the leaſt ſpark of grace: for though a man may through his hypocriſie, condemn that evil in another<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151476:18"/>which he allowes in himſelf: yet he cannot condemn the good, which himſelf is indued withal. For good cannot but rejoyce, and delight in her like.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Abſtract,</hi> being printed occaſionally, I am forced to uſe all poſſible brevity. And in caſe they would ſee more of this and the like, let them read <hi>The Cure of Mispriſion,</hi> or miſtake.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, I will humbly begg of God, upon the ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed knees of my ſoul; that theſe lines may not riſe up in judgment againſt thoſe <hi>Hazaels,</hi> that have read them, and are never the better: And ſo inſtead of curing their ſin, prove a meanes to increaſe their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>NOw conſidering the numberleſſe number of thoſe, that by profeſſing themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> diſcredit the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> That (becauſe they have been Chriſtned as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was, received the Sacrament like <hi>Judas,</hi> and for company go to Church alſo as <hi>Dogs</hi> do) are called <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> as we call the <hi>Heathen Images Gods.</hi> Yea, and (being blinded by the <hi>Prince of Darkneſſe,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.4.) think to be ſaved by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though they take up Armes againſt him; and are no more like <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> then <hi>Michals Image</hi> of Goates-hair was like <hi>David:</hi> That being <hi>Chriſtians in name,</hi> will ſcoffe at a <hi>Chriſtian indeed:</hi> That honour the <hi>dead Saints</hi> in a cold profeſſion, while they worry the <hi>living Saints</hi> in a cruel perſecution: That make the <hi>World</hi> onely their <hi>God;</hi> and pleaſure, or profit alone their <hi>Religion:</hi> That do what is morally good, more for fear of the <hi>Law,</hi> then for love of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> That fear the <hi>Mogiſtrate,</hi> more then they fear <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Devil;</hi> And a <hi>Priſon</hi> more, then <hi>Hell:</hi> That with <hi>Adam,</hi> will become <hi>Satans Bondſlaves</hi> for an <hi>Apple:</hi> And like <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſell their <hi>Birth-right</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> here, and their <hi>bleſſing</hi> of <hi>glory</hi> hereafter for a <hi>meſſe of Pottage.</hi> That like men ſleeping in a <hi>Boat;</hi> are carried down the ſtream of this <hi>World,</hi> untill they arrive at their <hi>Graves-end, [Death;]</hi> without once waking to bethink themſelves, whither they are going [to <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell.</hi>] As alſo in reference to <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.1. And out
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151476:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>of compaſſion to their precious <hi>ſoules;</hi> There are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at the place hereunder mentioned, eight ſeverall Books purpoſely compoſed, whereof one will be free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given, and the other ſeven lent <hi>gratis,</hi> to any that ſhall require them. Which Books (like Glaſſes) will ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w them (from <hi>Gods Word</hi>) the very faces of their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earts. And (like <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Act. 11.) <hi>tell them words whereby</hi> (with bleſſing from above,) <hi>both they and their</hi> Aſſociates (by their meanes) <hi>may be ſaved,</hi> verſe 14.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>At the <hi>Blew Pales,</hi> over againſt the High Conſtables ſhort of <hi>Shoreditch</hi> Church; where is a Glaſſe Lanthorn in the Window: ſuch as pleaſe may have them.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The names of the Books are theſe.</head>
               <item>A Hopeful way, to Cure that horrid ſin of <hi>Swearing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The odious, deſpicable, and dreadful condition of a <hi>Drunkard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Glaſſe, for <hi>Scoffers at Religion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Englands <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankfulneſſe,</hi> ſtriving with <hi>Gods goodneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Arraignment, and remedy of <hi>Covetouſneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Character, of a Formal <hi>Hypocrite.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Paſtors</hi> Advocate; and therein of <hi>preaching</hi> without a Call.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Whole Duty</hi> of a Chriſtian.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
